{"prelims": [{"question": "\u2018Gadgil Committee Report\u2019 and \u2018Kasturirangan Committee Report\u2019, sometimes seen in the news, are related to", "options": ["(a) constitutional reforms", "(b) Ganga Action Plan", "(c) linking of rivers", "(d) protection of Western Ghats"], "answer": "(d) protection of Western Ghats", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: D</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong>Clear-cut answer.</p>\n<p><a href=\"http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/home/environment/developmental-issues/Gadgil-committee-recommendations-on-Western-Ghats-ideal-practical-Experts/articleshow/41136674.cms\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\"></a><a href=\"http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/home/environment/developmental-issues/Gadgil-\" rel=\"nofollow ugc\">http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/home/environment/developmental-issues/Gadgil-</a> committee-recommendations-on-Western-Ghats-ideal-practical- Experts/articleshow/41136674.cms</p>\n<p><a href=\"http://www.business-standard.com/article/economy-policy/kasturirangan-report-to-be-basis-for-eco-sensitive-areas-in-western-ghats-114082701235_1.html\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\"></a><a href=\"http://www.business-standard.com/article/economy-policy/kasturirangan-report-to-be-\" rel=\"nofollow ugc\">http://www.business-standard.com/article/economy-policy/kasturirangan-report-to-be-</a> basis-for-eco-sensitive-areas-in-western-ghats-114082701235_1.html</p>\n                                "}, {"question": "With reference to \u2018Pradhan Mantri Fasal Bima Yojana\u2019, consider the following statements:\nUnder this scheme, farmers will have to pay a uniform premium of two percent for any crop they cultivate in any season of the year.\nThis scheme covers post-harvest losses arising out of cyclones and unseasonal rains.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?", "options": ["(a) 1 only", "(b) 2 only", "(c) Both 1 and 2", "(d) Neither 1 nor 2"], "answer": "(b) 2 only", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: B</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong>Only statement 2 is correct.</p>\n<ul>\n<li><strong>Statement 1:</strong> Farmers\u2019 premium has been kept at a maximum of 2 per cent for food grains and oilseeds, and up to 5 per cent for horticulture and cotton So, it is different for different crops. 1 is incorrect.</li>\n<li><strong>Statement 2:</strong> Post-Harvest Losses coverage is available only up to a maximum period of two weeks from harvesting for those crops which are allowed to dry in cut and spread condition in the field after harvesting against specific perils of cyclone and cyclonic rains and unseasonal rains. So, 2 is correct.</li>\n</ul>\n<p><strong>Source</strong>: <a href=\"https://india.gov.in/spotlight/pradhan-mantri-fasal-bima-yojana\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">https://india.gov.in/spotlight/pradhan-mantri-fasal-bima-yojana</a></p>\n                                "}, {"question": "Consider the following pairs :\nCommunity sometimes In the affairs of mentioned in the news\nKurd                              : Bangladesh\nMadhesi                       : Nepal\nRohingya                        : Myanmar\nWhich of the pairs given above is/are correctly matched?", "options": ["(a) 1 and 2", "b) 2 only", "(c) 2 and 3", "(d) 3 only"], "answer": "(c) 2 and 3", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: C</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong>Only 2 and 3 are correctly matched.</p>\n<ul>\n<li>Kurds are an ethnic group in the Middle East. So, 1 is incorrect.</li>\n<li>Madhesis were recently in news due to Nepal\u2019s constitutional debates about their representation in the polity. So, 2 is correct.</li>\n<li>Rohingya Muslims and Buddhist Rakhine have been indulging into fights and riots in Myanmar, which has frequently been in news. So, 3 is correct.</li>\n</ul>\n<p><strong>Source</strong>:</p>\n<ol>\n<li><a href=\"http://www.bbc.com/news/world-middle-east-29702440\">bbc.com/news/world-middle-east-29702440</a></li>\n<li><a href=\"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2015_Rohingya_refugee_crisis\">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2015_Rohingya_refugee_crisis</a></li>\n<li><a href=\"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Madhesi_people\">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Madhesi_people</a></li>\n</ol>\n                                "}, {"question": "What is/are the purpose/purposes of `District Mineral Foundations\u2019 in India?\nPromoting mineral exploration activities in mineral-rich districts\nProtecting the interests of the persons affected by mining operations\nAuthorizing State Governments to issue licences for mineral exploration\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below.", "options": ["(a) 1 and 2 only", "(b) 2 only", "(c) 1 and 3 only", "(d) 1, 2 and 3"], "answer": "(b) 2 only", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: B</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong>District Mineral Foundation (DMF) is a trust set up as a non-profit body, in those districts affected by the mining works, to work for the interest and benefit of persons and areas affected by mining related operations. It is funded through the contributions from miners.</p>\n<p>So, all other statements apart from 2 are wrong.</p>\n<p>Setting up of District Mineral Foundations (DMFs) in all districts in the country affected by mining related operations was mandated through the Mines and Minerals (Development &amp; Regulation) Amendment Act, (MMDRA) 2015.</p>\n<p>Its manner of operation comes under the jurisdiction of the relevant State Government.</p>\n<p><a href=\"http://www.arthapedia.in/index.php?title=District_Mineral_Foundation_(DMF)\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">http://www.arthapedia.in/index.php?title=District_Mineral_Foundation_(DMF)</a></p>\n                                "}, {"question": "The plan of Sir Stafford Cripps envisaged that after the Second World War", "options": ["(a) India should be granted complete independence", "(b) India should be partitioned into two before granting independence", "(c) India should be made a republic with the condition that she will join the Commonwealth", "(d) India should be given Dominion status"], "answer": "(d) India should be given Dominion status", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p></p><div id=\"wpwrap\">\n<div id=\"adminmenumain\" role=\"navigation\" aria-label=\"Main menu\">\n<h1>Solution: D</h1>\n<p><strong>Justification: Cripps</strong>&nbsp;worked to keep India loyal to the British war effort in exchange for a promise of elections and full self-government (<strong>Dominion status</strong>) once the war was over.</p>\n<p><strong>Source: </strong>Standard question on Cripps Mission. NCERT \u2013 12<sup>th</sup> \u2013 Themes in Indian History \u2013 III</p>\n</div>\n</div>\n<p></p>                                "}, {"question": "The term \u2018Core Banking Solutions\u2019 is sometimes seen in the news. Which of the following statements best describes/describe this term?\nIt is a networking of a bank\u2019s branches which enables customers to operate their accounts from any branch of the bank on its network regardless of where they open their accounts.\nIt is an effort to increase RBI\u2019s control over commercial banks through computerization.\nIt is a detailed procedure by which a bank with huge non- performing assets is taken over by another bank.\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below.", "options": ["(a) 1 only", "(b) 2 and 3 only", "(c) 1 and 3 only", "(d) 1, 2 and 3"], "answer": "(a) 1 only", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: A</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong><u>Statement 1:</u> Core Banking Solution (CBS) is networking of branches, which enables Customers to operate their accounts, and avail banking services from any branch of the Bank on CBS network, regardless of where he maintains his account.</p>\n<p>Clearly, 1 is correct.</p>\n<p><u>Statement 2 and</u> 3: They are absurd and can easily be eliminated.</p>\n<p><a href=\"http://www.bankofbaroda.co.in/cbs.asp\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">http://www.bankofbaroda.co.in/cbs.asp</a></p>\n                                "}, {"question": "What is/are unique about \u2018Kharai Camel\u2019, a breed found in India?\nIt is capable of swimming up to three kilometres in seawater.\nIt survives by grazing on mangroves.\nIt lives in the wild and cannot be domesticated.\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below.", "options": ["(a) 1 and 2 only", "(b) 3 only", "(c) 1 and 3 only", "(d) 1, 2 and 3"], "answer": "(a) 1 and 2 only", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: A</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong><u>Statement 1 and 2:</u> It can swim up to three kilometers into the sea in search of mangroves, its primary food.</p>\n<p>The breed population has declined drastically in recent years due to loss of mangroves.</p>\n<p><u>Statement</u> 3: Given the breed\u2019s ability to survive both on land and sea, the Kharai camel is one of the most preferred choices of graziers in the arid coastal region of Kachchh.</p>\n<p>People consume its milk, while male calves are sold for economic returns (females are not sold because they are considered sacred). So, clearly they are domesticated and don\u2019t live in the wild. Statement 3 is wrong.</p>\n<p>Gujarat is the only home to Kharai camel.</p>\n<p><a href=\"http://www.downtoearth.org.in/coverage/the-sinking-ship-40705\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">http://www.downtoearth.org.in/coverage/the-sinking-ship-40705</a></p>\n                                "}, {"question": "The term \u2018Regional Comprehensive Economic Partnership\u2019 often appears in the news in the context of the affairs of a group of countries known as", "options": ["(a) G20", "(b) ASEAN", "(c) SCO", "(d) SAARC"], "answer": "(b) ASEAN", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: B</p>\n<p><strong>Justification:</strong></p>\n<p>The Regional Comprehensive Economic Partnership (<strong>RCEP</strong>) is a trade agreement between the member states of the Association of Southeast Asian Nations (<strong>ASEAN</strong>) and its free trade agreement (FTA) partners (recently, India walked out of RCEP negotiations)</p>\n<p><strong>Source</strong>: <a href=\"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Regional_Comprehensive_Economic_Partnership\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Regional_Comprehensive_Economic_Partnership</a></p>\n                                "}, {"question": "With reference to `Astrosat\u2019, the astronomical observatory launched by India, which of the following statements is/are correct?\nOther than USA and Russia, India is the only country to have launched a similar observatory into space.\nAstrosat is a 2000 kg satellite placed in an orbit at 1650 km above the surface of the\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below.", "options": ["a) 1 only", "(b) 2 only", "(c) Both 1 and 2", "(d) Neither 1 nor 2"], "answer": "(d) Neither 1 nor 2", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: D</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong>Neither 1 nor 2 are correct.</p>\n<p>ASTROSAT is India\u2019s first dedicated multi wavelength space observatory.</p>\n<p><u>Statement 1:</u> This is the first time ISRO is launching a space observatory into space. Before India, NASA, space agencies of the European Union, Japan and Russia have launched similar facilities into the space. So, 1 is wrong.</p>\n<p><u>Statement 2:</u> ASTROSAT with a lift-off mass of about 1513 kg was launched into a 650 km orbit (polar). So, 2 is wrong.</p>\n<p><strong>Source</strong>:</p>\n<ol>\n<li><a href=\"http://www.isro.gov.in/Spacecraft/astrosat\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">http://www.isro.gov.in/Spacecraft/astrosat</a></li>\n<li><a href=\"http://www.thehindu.com/sci-tech/science/isro-launches-astrosat-first-space-observatory/article7697707.ece\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">http://www.thehindu.com/sci-tech/science/isro-launches-astrosat-first-space-observatory/article7697707.ece</a></li>\n<li><a href=\"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_space_telescopes\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_space_telescopes</a></li>\n</ol>\n                                "}, {"question": "Regarding DigiLocker\u2019, sometimes seen in the news, which of the following statements is/are correct?\nIt is a digital locker system offered by the Government under Digital India\nIt allows you to access your e-documents irrespective of your physical location.\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below.", "options": ["(a) 1 only", "(b) 2 only", "(c) Both 1 and 2", "(d) Neither 1 nor 2"], "answer": "(c) Both 1 and 2", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: C</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong>Both the statements are correct.</p>\n<ul>\n<li>DigiLocker is one of the key initiatives under the Digital India Programme. This was released by the Department of Electronics and Information Technology (DeitY), Government of India.</li>\n<li>The space can be utilized for storing personal documents like University certificates, Permanent account number (PAN) cards, voter id cards, etc., and the URIs of the e- documents issued by various issuer departments.</li>\n</ul>\n<p><strong>Source</strong>: <a href=\"https://india.gov.in/spotlight/digilocker-online-document-storage-facility\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">https://india.gov.in/spotlight/digilocker-online-document-storage-facility</a></p>\n                                "}, {"question": "Banjaras during the medieval period of Indian history were generally", "options": ["(a) agriculturists", "(b) warriors", "(c) weavers", "(d) traders"], "answer": "(d) traders", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: D</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong>There were many different tribal groups in Medieval India. Some were hunter-gatherer nomads.</p>\n<p>One such type of nomadic group was that of the banjaras.</p>\n<p>They were the most important trader-nomads during the medieval period.</p>\n<p>Their caravan was called tanda. Sultan Alauddin Khaljls market regulation system could become successful pnmanly because of the fact that he relied heavily on the banjaras to transport grains to the city markets.</p>\n<p><a href=\"http://tinyurl.com/j7ejmq8\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">http://tinyurl.com/j7ejmq8</a></p>\n                                "}, {"question": "Which of the following is not a member of `Gulf Cooperation Council\u2019?", "options": ["(a) Iran", "(b) Saudi Arabia", "(c) Oman", "(d) Kuwait"], "answer": "(a) Iran", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: A</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong>It is a political and economic alliance of six Middle Eastern countries\u2014 Saudi Arabia, Kuwait, the United Arab Emirates, Qatar, Bahrain, and Oman.</p>\n<p><a href=\"https://www.mea.gov.in/Portal/ForeignRelation/Gulf_Cooperation_Council_MEA_Website.pdf\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\"></a><a href=\"https://www.mea.gov.in/Portal/ForeignRelation/Gulf_Cooperation_Council_MEA_Web\" rel=\"nofollow ugc\">https://www.mea.gov.in/Portal/ForeignRelation/Gulf_Cooperation_Council_MEA_Web</a> site.pdf</p>\n                                "}, {"question": "With reference to \u2018Financial Stability and Development Council\u2019, consider the following statements :\nIt is an organ of NITI Aayog.\nIt is headed by the Union Finance Minister.\nIt monitors macro-prudential supervision of the economy.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?", "options": ["(a) 1 and 2 only", "(b) 3 only", "(c) 2 and 3 only", "(d) 1, 2 and 3"], "answer": "(c) 2 and 3 only", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: C</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong><u>Statement 1:</u> With a view to strengthening and institutionalizing the mechanism for maintaining financial stability, enhancing inter-regulatory coordination and promoting financial sector development, the Financial Stability and Development Council (FSDC) was set up by the Government as the apex level forum in December 2010 (much before NITI AAyog was even setup). So, 1 is incorrect.</p>\n<p><u>Statement 2:</u> The Chairman of the Council is the Finance Minister and its members include the heads of financial sector Regulators (RBI, SEBI, PFRDA, IRDA &amp; FMC) Finance Secretary and/or Secretary, Department of Economic Affairs, Secretary, Department of Financial Services, and Chief Economic Adviser. So, 2 is correct.</p>\n<p><u>Statement</u> 3<u>:</u> Without prejudice to the autonomy of regulators, the Council monitors macro prudential supervision of the economy, including functioning of large financial conglomerates, and addresses inter-regulatory coordination and financial sector development issues. So, 3 is correct.</p>\n<p>It also focuses on financial literacy and financial inclusion.</p>\n<p><a href=\"http://finmin.nic.in/fsdc/StrucFSDC.pdf\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">http://finmin.nic.in/fsdc/StrucFSDC.pdf</a></p>\n                                "}, {"question": "India\u2019s ranking in the \u2018Ease of Doing Business Index\u2019 is sometimes seen in the news. Which of the following has declared that ranking?", "options": ["(a) Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development (OECD)", "(b) World Economic Forum", "(c) World Bank", "(d) World Trade Organization (WTO)"], "answer": "(c) World Bank", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: C</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong><a href=\"http://economictimes.indiatimes.com/definition/ease-of-doing-business\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">http://economictimes.indiatimes.com/definition/ease-of-doing-business</a></p>\n                                "}, {"question": "Who of the following had first deciphered the edicts of Emperor Ashoka?", "options": ["(a) Georg Bilhler", "(b) James Prinsep", "(c) Max Muller", "(d) William Jones"], "answer": "(b) James Prinsep", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: B</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong>Factual but straightforward <a href=\"https://www.cs.colostate.edu/~malaiya/ashoka.html\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">https://www.cs.colostate.edu/~malaiya/ashoka.html</a></p>\n                                "}, {"question": "\u2018Net metering\u2019 is sometimes seen in the news in the context of promoting the", "options": ["(a) production and use of solar energy by the households/consumers", "(b) use of piped natural gas in the kitchens of households", "(c) installation of CNG kits in motor-cars", "(d) installation of water meters in urban households"], "answer": "(a) production and use of solar energy by the households/consumers", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: A</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong>Net metering is a billing mechanism that credits solar energy system owners for the electricity they add to the grid, if you generate more energy (from household solar rooftops) than you consume in home.</p>\n<p><a href=\"http://www.mass.gov/eea/grants-and-tech-assistance/guidance-technical-assistance/agencies-and-divisions/dpu/net-metering-faqs.html\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\"></a><a href=\"http://www.mass.gov/eea/grants-and-tech-assistance/guidance-technical-\" rel=\"nofollow ugc\">http://www.mass.gov/eea/grants-and-tech-assistance/guidance-technical-</a> assistance/agencies-and-divisions/dpu/net-metering-faqs.html</p>\n                                "}, {"question": "With reference to the \u2018Trans-Pacific Partnership\u2019, consider the following statements :\nIt is an agreement among all the Pacific Rim countries except China and Russia.\nIt is a strategic alliance for the purpose of maritime security only.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?", "options": ["(a) 1 only", "(b) 2 only", "(c) Both 1 and 2", "(d) Neither 1 nor 2"], "answer": "(d) Neither 1 nor 2", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: D</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong><u>Statement 1:</u> It involves 12 pacific-rim countries: the US, Japan, Malaysia, Vietnam, Singapore, Brunei, Australia, New Zealand, Canada, Mexico, Chile and Peru.</p>\n<p>It\u2019s no an agreement between ALL the Pacific Rim except Russia &amp; China. Only 12 out of nearly 50+ Pacific Rim countries are part of it.</p>\n<p><u>Statement 2:</u> It is a trade bloc. So, 2 is wrong.</p>\n<p><a href=\"https://ustr.gov/tpp/\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">https://ustr.gov/tpp/</a></p>\n                                "}, {"question": "The `Swadeshi\u2019 and \u2018Boycott\u2019 were adopted as methods of struggle for the first time during the", "options": ["(a) agitation against the Partition of Bengal", "(b) Home Rule Movement", "(c) Non-Cooperation Movement", "(d) visit of the Simon Commission to India"], "answer": "(a) agitation against the Partition of Bengal", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: A</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong>Straightforward answer.</p>\n                                "}, {"question": "Which of the following is/are included in the capital budget of the Government of India?\nExpenditure on acquisition of assets like roads, buildings, machinery, etc.\nLoans received from foreign governments\nLoans and advances granted to the States and Union Territories Select the\ncorrect answer using the code given below.", "options": ["(a) 1 only", "(b) 2 and 3 only", "(c) 1 and 3 only", "(d) 1,2 and 3"], "answer": "(d) 1,2 and 3", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: D</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong>All the statements are correct.</p>\n<ul>\n<li>The Capital Budget is an account of the assets as well as liabilities of the central government, which takes into consideration changes in capital \u2013 both capital expenditure and capital receipt.</li>\n<li>The main items of capital receipts are loans raised by the government from the public which are called market borrowings, borrowing by the government from the Reserve Bank and commercial banks and other financial institutions through the sale of treasury bills, loans received from foreign governments and international organisations, and recoveries of loans granted by the central government. So, 2 is correct.</li>\n<li>Capital Expenditure includes expenditure on the acquisition of land, building, machinery, and equipment, investment in shares, and loans and advances by the central government to state and union territory governments, PSUs and other parties. So, 1 and 3 are correct.</li>\n</ul>\n<p><strong>Source: </strong>12<sup>th</sup> NCERT Macroeconomics</p>\n                                "}, {"question": "What is/are the purpose/purposes of the `Marginal Cost of Funds based Lending Rate (MCLR)\u2019 announced by RBI?\nThese guidelines help improve the transparency in the methodology followed by banks for determining the interest rates on advances.\nThese guidelines help ensure availability of bank credit at interest rates which are fair to the borrowers as well as the banks.\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below.", "options": ["(a) 1 only", "(b) 2 only", "(c) Both 1 and 2", "(d) Neither 1 nor 2"], "answer": "(c) Both 1 and 2", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p></p><div id=\"wpwrap\">\n<div id=\"adminmenumain\" role=\"navigation\" aria-label=\"Main menu\">\n<p>Solution: C</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong>It is the new benchmark lending rate at which banks will now lend to new borrowers.</p>\n<p><u>Statement 1:</u> MCLR will be calculated after factoring in banks\u2019 marginal cost of funds (largely, the interest at which banks borrow money), return on equity (a measure of banks\u2019 profitability), and other risks and costs.</p>\n<p>The MCLR should be revised monthly by considering some new factors including the repo rate and other borrowing rates.</p>\n<p>Specifically the repo rate and other borrowing rates that were not explicitly considered under the base rate system.</p>\n<p>Banks will also publically publish all kinds of MCLR periodically.</p>\n<p>This will surely bring transparency in the calculation methodology. So, 1 is correct. The RBI expects the new formula to make floating lending rates more responsive to its policy rate cuts.</p>\n<p><u>Statement 2:</u> Based upon this MCLR, interest rate for different types of customers should be fixed in <u>accordance with their riskiness</u>. So, it become fair to both borrowers as well as lenders.</p>\n<p><a href=\"https://rbi.org.in/SCRIPTs/BS_PressReleaseDisplay.aspx?prid=35749\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">https://rbi.org.in/SCRIPTs/BS_PressReleaseDisplay.aspx?prid=35749</a></p>\n</div>\n</div>\n<p></p>                                "}, {"question": "Consider the following statements:\nThe International Solar Alliance was launched at the United Nations Climate Change Conference in\nThe Alliance includes all the member countries of the United Nations.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?", "options": ["(a) 1 only", "(b) 2 only", "(c) Both 1 and 2", "(d) Neither 1 nor 2"], "answer": "(a) 1 only", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: A</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong>Only statement 1 is correct.</p>\n<ul>\n<li>India and France have launched an International Solar Alliance at the UN Climate Change Conference in Paris to boost solar energy in developing countries. So, 1 is correct.</li>\n<li>The alliance includes around 120 countries (not all UN members) that support the \u201cDeclaration on the occasion to launch the international solar alliance of countries dedicated to the promotion of solar energy\u201d. So, statement 2 is wrong.</li>\n</ul>\n<p><strong>Source</strong>: <a href=\"http://newsroom.unfccc.int/clean-energy/international-solar-energy-alliance-launched-at-cop21/\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">http://newsroom.unfccc.int/clean-energy/international-solar-energy-alliance-launched-at-cop21/</a></p>\n                                "}, {"question": "Consider the following pairs:\nTerms sometimes                    Their origin seen in the news\nAnnex\u2014I Countries                                            :     Cartagena Protocol\nCertified Emissions Reductions          : Nagoya Protocol\nClean Development Mechanism               : Kyoto Protocol\nWhich of the pairs given above is/are correctly matched?", "options": ["(a) 1 and 2 only", "(b) 2 and 3 only", "(c) 3 only", "(d) 1, 2 and 3"], "answer": "(c) 3 only", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: C</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong><u>Statement 1:</u> Annex-I countries are related to Kyoto Protocol. See <a href=\"http://unfccc.int/kyoto_protocol/items/3145.php\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">http://unfccc.int/kyoto_protocol/items/3145.php</a></p>\n<p><u>Statement 2:</u> A certified emission reduction (CER) is generated from a clean development mechanism (CDM) project activity. See <a href=\"http://unfccc.int/kyoto_protocol/mechanisms/clean_development_mechanism/items/2718.php\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\"></a><a href=\"http://unfccc.int/kyoto_protocol/mechanisms/clean_development_mechanism/items/2\" rel=\"nofollow ugc\">http://unfccc.int/kyoto_protocol/mechanisms/clean_development_mechanism/items/2</a> 718.php</p>\n<p><u>Statement</u> 3<u>:</u> Same link as above.</p>\n                                "}, {"question": "\u2018Mission Indradhanush\u2019 launched by the Government of India pertains to", "options": ["(a) immunization of children and pregnant women", "(b) construction of smart cities across the country", "(c) India\u2019s own search for the Earth-like planets in outer space", "(d) New Educational Policy"], "answer": "(a) immunization of children and pregnant women", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: A</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong><a href=\"http://pib.nic.in/newsite/PrintRelease.aspx?relid=114103\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">http://pib.nic.in/newsite/PrintRelease.aspx?relid=114103</a></p>\n                                "}, {"question": "\u2018RashtriyaGarimaAbhiyaan\u2019 is a national campaign to", "options": ["(a) rehabilitate the homeless and destitute persons and provide them with suitable sources of livelihood", "(b) release the sex workers from their practice and provide them with alternative sources of livelihood", "(c) eradicate the practice of manual scavenging and rehabilitate the manual scavengers", "(d) release the bonded labourers from their bondage and rehabilitate them"], "answer": "(c) eradicate the practice of manual scavenging and rehabilitate the manual scavengers", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: C</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong>It is the \u201cNational Campaign for Dignity and Eradication of Manual Scavenging\u201d.</p>\n<p><a href=\"http://pib.nic.in/newsite/efeatures.aspx?relid=126057\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">http://pib.nic.in/newsite/efeatures.aspx?relid=126057</a></p>\n                                "}, {"question": "\u2018European Stability Mechanism\u2019, sometimes seen in the news, is an", "options": ["(a) agency created by EU to deal with the impact of millions of refugees arriving from Middle East", "(b) agency of EU that provides financial assistance to eurozone countries", "(c) agency of EU to deal with all the bilateral and multilateral agreements on trade", "(d) agency of EU to deal with the conflicts arising among the member countries"], "answer": "(b) agency of EU that provides financial assistance to eurozone countries", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: B</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong>The European Stability Mechanism is a European Union agency that provides financial assistance, in the form of loans, to euro-zone countries or as new capital to banks in difficulty.</p>\n<p><strong>Source</strong>: <a href=\"http://www.esm.europa.eu/\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">http://www.esm.europa.eu/</a></p>\n                                "}, {"question": "\u2018Project Loon\u2019, sometimes seen in the news, is related to", "options": ["(a) waste management technology", "(b) wireless communication technology", "(c) solar power production technology", "(d) water conservation technology"], "answer": "(b) wireless communication technology", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: B</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong>Project Loon aims to help connect remote regions of the world to the internet via a network of balloons floating in the sky beaming internet.</p>\n<p><a href=\"http://economictimes.indiatimes.com/tech/internet/google-may-get-government-nod-to-conduct-pilot-for-project-loon-in-india/articleshow/52408455.cms\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\"></a><a href=\"http://economictimes.indiatimes.com/tech/internet/google-may-get-government-nod-\" rel=\"nofollow ugc\">http://economictimes.indiatimes.com/tech/internet/google-may-get-government-nod-</a> to-conduct-pilot-for-project-loon-in-india/articleshow/52408455.cms</p>\n                                "}, {"question": "Which of the following statements is/are correct?\nA Bill pending in the LokSabha lapses on its prorogation.\nA Bill pending in the Rajya Sabha, which has not been passed by the LokSabha, shall not lapse on dissolution of the LokSabha.\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below.", "options": ["(a) 1 only", "b) 2 only", "(c) Both 1 and 2", "(d) Neither 1 nor 2"], "answer": "b) 2 only", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: B</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong>Only statement 2 is correct.</p>\n<ul>\n<li><strong>Statement 1</strong>: Prorogation does not affect the bills or any other business pending before the House. It is the pending notices (other than those for introducing bills) that lapse on prorogation and fresh notices have to be given for the next session. So, 1 is incorrect.</li>\n<li><strong>Statement 2:</strong> A bill pending in the LokSabha lapses (whether originating in the LokSabha or transmitted to it by the Rajya Sabha).</li>\n<li>A bill passed by the LokSabha but pending in the Rajya Sabha lapses.</li>\n<li>A bill pending in the Rajya Sabha but not passed by the LokSabha does not A bill passed by both Houses but pending assent of the president does not lapse So, 2 is correct.</li>\n</ul>\n<p><strong>Source: </strong>Indian Polity: M Laxmikanth</p>\n                                "}, {"question": "In which of the following regions of India are shale gas resources found?\nCambay Basin\nCauvery Basin\nKrishna-Godavari Basin\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below.", "options": ["(a) 1 and 2 only", "(b) 3 only", "(c) 2 and 3 only", "(d) 1, 2 and 3"], "answer": "(d) 1, 2 and 3", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: D</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong>The Ministry of Petroleum and Natural Gas (MoPNG) has identified six basins as potentially shale gas bearing. These are Cambay, Assam-Arakan, Gondwana, Krishna-Godavari, Kaveri, and the Indo-Gangetic plain.</p>\n<p><a href=\"http://www.teriin.org/policybrief/docs/Shale_gas.pdf\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">http://www.teriin.org/policybrief/docs/Shale_gas.pdf</a></p>\n                                "}, {"question": "Which of the following are the key features of \u2018National Ganga River Basin Authority (NGRBA)?\nRiver basin is the unit of planning and management.\nIt spearheads the river conservation efforts at the national level.\nOne of the Chief Ministers of the States through which the Ganga flows becomes the Chairman of NGRBA on rotation basis.\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below.", "options": ["(a) 1 and 2 only", "(b) 2 and 3 only", "(c) 1 and 3 only", "(d) 1,2 and 3"], "answer": "(a) 1 and 2 only", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p></p><div id=\"wpwrap\">\n<div id=\"adminmenumain\" role=\"navigation\" aria-label=\"Main menu\">\n<h1>Solution: A</h1>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong>Only statement 1 and 2 correct.</p>\n<ul>\n<li>The statements 1 and 2 were picked verbatim from CPCB Website, we quote, \u201cRiver basin will be the unit of planning and management. This is an internationally accepted strategy for integrated management of rivers.</li>\n<li>Accordingly, a new institutional mechanism in the form of National Ganga River Basin Authority (NGRBA) will spearhead river conservation efforts at the national level.</li>\n<li>Implementation will be by the State Agencies and Urban Local Bodies\u201d.</li>\n<li>Statement 3: PM Chairs the NGRBA.</li>\n</ul>\n<p><strong>Source</strong>: <a href=\"http://cpcb.nic.in/ngrba/about.html\">http://cpcb.nic.in/ngrba/about.html</a></p>\n</div>\n</div>\n<p></p>                                "}, {"question": "\u2018Global Financial Stability Report\u2019 is prepared by the", "options": ["(a) European Central Bank", "(b) International Monetary Fund", "(c) International Bank for Reconstruction and Development", "(d) Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development"], "answer": "(b) International Monetary Fund", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: B</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong><a href=\"https://www.imf.org/external/pubs/ft/gfsr/\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">https://www.imf.org/external/pubs/ft/gfsr/</a></p>\n                                "}, {"question": "With reference to the religious history of India, consider the following statements :\nThe concept of Bodhisattva is central to Hinayana sect of Buddhism.\nBodhisattva is a compassionate one on his way to enlightenment.\nBodhisattva delays achieving his own salvation to help all sentient beings on their path to it.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?", "options": ["(a) 1 only", "(b) 2 and 3 only", "(c) 2 only", "(d) 1, 2 and 3"], "answer": "(b) 2 and 3 only", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: B</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong><u>Statement 1:</u> It is central to the Mahayana sect of Buddhism.</p>\n<p>In non-Mahayana Buddhism, it usually refers either to Maitreya, the Buddha of the Future, or to the historical Buddha Gautama prior to his enlightenment.</p>\n<p><u>Statement 2 and</u> 3<u>:</u> A bodhisattva is literally a living being (sattva) who aspires to enlightenment (bodhi) and carries out altruistic practices. The bodhisattva ideal is central to the Mahayana Buddhist tradition as the individual who seeks enlightenment both for him- or herself and for others. Clearly 2 is correct.</p>\n<p>Compassion, an empathetic sharing of the sufferings of others, is the bodhisattva\u2019s greatest characteristic.</p>\n<p>It is held that the bodhisattva makes four vows expressing a determination to work for the happiness of others: \u201cHowever innumerable sentient beings are, I vow to save them; however inexhaustible the passions are, I vow to master them; however limitless the teachings are, I vow to study them; however infinite the Buddha-truth is, I vow to attain it.\u201d</p>\n<p>Clearly 3 is correct.</p>\n<p><a href=\"http://www.sgi.org/about-us/buddhism-in-daily-life/bodhisattva.html\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">http://www.sgi.org/about-us/buddhism-in-daily-life/bodhisattva.html</a></p>\n                                "}, {"question": "With reference to the \u2018Gram Nyayalaya Act\u2019, which of the following statements is/are correct?\nAs per the Act, Gram Nyayalayas can hear only civil cases and not criminal cases.\nThe Act allows local social activists as mediators/reconciliators.\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below.", "options": ["(a) 1 only", "(b) 2 only", "(c) Both 1 and 2", "(d) Neither 1 nor 2"], "answer": "(b) 2 only", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: B</p>\n<p><u>Statement 1:</u> It tries both Civil and Criminal cases. So, 1 is wrong.</p>\n<p><u>Statement 2:</u> We are quoting from the Gram Nyalayas Act, 2008</p>\n<p>\u201c27. (1) For the purposes of section 26, the District Court shall, in consultation with the Appointment District Magistrate, prepare a panel consisting of the names of social workers at the village level having integrity for appointment as Conciliators who possess such qualifications and experience as may be prescribed by the High Court.\u201d</p>\n<p>So, clearly 2 is correct.</p>\n<p><a href=\"http://doj.gov.in/sites/default/files/gramnyayalayas_0.pdf\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">http://doj.gov.in/sites/default/files/gramnyayalayas_0.pdf</a></p>\n                                "}, {"question": "With reference to pre-packaged items in India, it is mandatory to the manufacturer to put which of the following information on the main label, as per the Food Safety and Standards (Packaging and Labelling) Regulations, 2011?\nList of ingredients including additives\nNutrition information\nRecommendations, if any, made by the medical profession about the possibility of any allergic reactions\nVegetarian/non-vegetarian\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below.", "options": ["(a) 1, 2 and 3", "(b) 2, 3 and 4", "(c) 1, 2 and 4", "(d) 1 and 4 only"], "answer": "(c) 1, 2 and 4", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: C</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong>Straightforward question. Information about Allergic reactions is NOT mandatory on the food packets.</p>\n<p><a href=\"http://www.fssai.gov.in/Portals/0/Pdf/Food%20Safety%20and%20standards%20(Packaging%20and%20Labelling)%20regulation%2C%202011.pdf\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\"></a><a href=\"http://www.fssai.gov.in/Portals/0/Pdf/Food%20Safety%20and%20standards%20(Packa\" rel=\"nofollow ugc\">http://www.fssai.gov.in/Portals/0/Pdf/Food%20Safety%20and%20standards%20(Packa</a> ging%20and%20Labelling)%20regulation,%202011.pdf</p>\n                                "}, {"question": "With reference to \u2018Bitcoins\u2019, sometimes seen in the news, which of the following statements is/are correct?\nBitcoins are tracked by the Central Banks of the countries.\nAnyone with a Bitcoin address can send and receive Bitcoins from anyone else with a Bitcoin address.\nOnline payments can be sent without either side knowing the identity of the other.\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below.", "options": ["(a) 1 and 2 only", "(b) 2 and 3 only", "(c) 3 only", "(d) 1, 2 and 3"], "answer": "(b) 2 and 3 only", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: B</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong>Bitcoins can be sent directly to anyone, anywhere in the world. The only requirement is that you should have a Bitcoin address of the recipient. The process doesn\u2019t require you to reveal your identity. So, 2 and 3 are correct.</p>\n<p>The system is peer-to-peer and transactions take place between users directly, without an intermediary. So, it is not tracked by the Central bank or any intermediary. 1 is incorrect.</p>\n<p><a href=\"https://bitcoin.org/en/how-it-works\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">https://bitcoin.org/en/how-it-works</a></p>\n                                "}, {"question": "Which of the following statements is/are correct?\nProper design and effective implementation of UN-REDD+ Programme can significantly contribute to\nprotection of biodiversity\nresilience of forest ecosystems\npoverty reduction\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below.", "options": ["(a) 1 and 2 only", "(b) 3 only", "(c) 2 and 3 only", "(d) 1, 2 and 3"], "answer": "(d) 1, 2 and 3", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: D</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong>Statement 3 was debatable, but we are posting verbatim from the source below,</p>\n<p>\u201cThe UN-REDD Programme has identified the following three topics for supporting national REDD+ governance structures, with an overarching principle of stakeholder participation</p>\n<p>Country-led multi-stakeholder governance assessments that contribute to the development and implementation of national REDD+ strategies (for tackling forest degradation and biodiversity loss) and nationally owned monitoring frameworks Social standards, including poverty and gender</p>\n<p>Land and/or carbon tenure and the role of REDD+ within national land use strategies</p>\n<p><a href=\"http://www.unep.org/forests/Portals/142/docs/UN-REDD%20Programme%20Strategy.pdf\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\"></a><a href=\"http://www.unep.org/forests/Portals/142/docs/UN-\" rel=\"nofollow ugc\">http://www.unep.org/forests/Portals/142/docs/UN-</a> REDD%20Programme%20Strategy.pdf</p>\n                                "}, {"question": "Which one of the following is a purpose of `UDAY\u2019, a scheme of the Government?", "options": ["(a) Providing technical and financial assistance to start-up entrepreneurs in the field of renewable sources of energy", "(b) Providing electricity to every household in the country by 2018", "(c) Replacing the coal-based power plants with natural gas, nuclear, solar, wind and tidal power plants over a period of time", "(d) Providing for financial turnaround and revival of power distribution companies"], "answer": "(d) Providing for financial turnaround and revival of power distribution companies", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: D</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong>It is the Ujwal DISCOM Assurance Yojana, where DISCOMs stand for distribution companies (electricity) that are state-owned and suffering huge financial losses due to poor infrastructure, AT&amp;C losses, mis-governance, low tariff rates etc.</p>\n<p>The scheme aims at their financial turnaround and revival.</p>\n<p><strong>Source: </strong>Ministry of Power Website</p>\n                                "}, {"question": "With reference to \u2018Li-Fi\u2019, recently in the news, which of the following statements is/are correct?\nIt uses light as the medium for high-speed data transmission.\nIt is a wireless technology and is several times faster than \u2018WiFi\u2019.\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below.", "options": ["a) 1 only", "(b) 2 only", "(c) Both 1 and 2", "(d) Neither 1 nor 2"], "answer": "(c) Both 1 and 2", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: C</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong>Both the statements are correct.</p>\n<ul>\n<li><strong>Statement 1:</strong> Li-Fi is loosely expanded to Light-Fidelity. Using precisely controlled light modulation, data can be transmitted using regular, visible light.</li>\n<li><strong>Statement 2:</strong> It will be 10-100 times faster than current-generation WiFi, and also very</li>\n</ul>\n<p><strong>Source</strong>: <a href=\"http://www.sciencealert.com/li-fi-tested-in-the-real-world-for-the-first-time-is-100-times-faster-than-wi-fi\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">http://www.sciencealert.com/li-fi-tested-in-the-real-world-for-the-first-time-is-100-times-faster-than-wi-fi</a></p>\n                                "}, {"question": "With reference to \u2018Organization for the Prohibition of Chemical Weapons (OPCW)\u2019, consider the following statements :\nIt is an organization of European Union in working relation with NATO and WHO.\nIt monitors chemical industry to prevent new weapons from emerging.\nIt provides assistance and protection to States (Parties) against chemical weapons threats.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?", "options": ["(a) 1 only", "(b) 2 and 3 only", "(c) 1 and 3 only", "(d) 1,2 and 3"], "answer": "(b) 2 and 3 only", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: B</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong>Only statement 2 and 3 are correct.</p>\n<p><strong>Statement 1:</strong> The Organisation for the Prohibition of Chemical Weapons is the implementing body of the Chemical Weapons Convention (CWC). It is not under EU. So, 1 is wrong.</p>\n<p><strong>Statement 2 and 3:</strong> The OPCW Member States share the collective goal of preventing chemistry from ever again being used for warfare, thereby strengthening international security.</p>\n<p>To this end, the Convention contains the below key provisions:</p>\n<ol>\n<li>Destroying all existing chemical weapons under international verification by the OPCW;</li>\n<li>Monitoring chemical industry to prevent new weapons from re-emerging; providing assistance and protection to States Parties against chemical threats; and</li>\n<li>Fostering international cooperation to strengthen implementation of the Convention and promote the peaceful use of chemistry.</li>\n</ol>\n<p><strong>Source</strong>: <a href=\"https://www.opcw.org/about-opcw/\">https://www.opcw.org/about-opcw/</a></p>\n                                "}, {"question": "`SWAYAM\u2019, an initiative of the Government of India, aims at", "options": ["(a) promoting the Self Help Groups in rural areas", "(b) providing financial and technical assistance to young start-up entrepreneurs", "(c) promoting the education and health of adolescent girls", "(d) providing affordable and quality education to the citizens for free"], "answer": "(d) providing affordable and quality education to the citizens for free", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p></p><div id=\"wpwrap\">\n<div id=\"adminmenumain\" role=\"navigation\" aria-label=\"Main menu\">\n<p>Solution: D</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong>SWAYAM is an Information Technology platform which will host Massive Open Online Courses (MOOCs) and provide high quality education on various subjects from school level\u2013class 9-12 to Under Graduate and Post Graduate students\u2013 covering all disciplines.</p>\n<p>Through this scheme the Ministry has proposed to provide high quality e-content to all colleges and universities free of cost.</p>\n<p><a href=\"http://economictimes.indiatimes.com/industry/services/education/pm-narendra-modi-to-launch-swayam-massive-open-online-courses-platform-on-aug-15/articleshow/53029959.cms\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\"></a><a href=\"http://economictimes.indiatimes.com/industry/services/education/pm-narendra-modi-\" rel=\"nofollow ugc\">http://economictimes.indiatimes.com/industry/services/education/pm-narendra-modi-</a> to-launch-swayam-massive-open-online-courses-platform-on-aug- 15/articleshow/53029959.cms</p>\n</div>\n</div>\n<p></p>                                "}, {"question": "The establishment of \u2018Payment Banks\u2019 is being allowed in India to promote financial inclusion. Which of the following statements is/are correct in this context?\nMobile telephone companies and supermarket chains that are owned and controlled by residents are eligible to be promoters of Payment Banks.\nPayment Banks can issue both credit cards and debit cards.\nPayment Banks cannot undertake lending activities.\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below.", "options": ["(a) 1 and 2 only", "(b) 1 and 3 only", "(c) 2 only", "(d) 1,2 and 3"], "answer": "(b) 1 and 3 only", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: B</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong>Only statement 1 and 3 are correct.</p>\n<p><strong>Statement 1:</strong> Eligible promoters (mentioning only some of them):</p>\n<ul>\n<li>Existing non-bank Pre-paid Payment Instrument (PPI) issuers; and other entities such as individuals / professionals; Non-Banking Finance Companies (NBFCs), corporate Business Correspondents(BCs), mobile telephone companies, super-market chains, companies, real sector cooperatives; that are owned and controlled by residents; and public sector entities may apply to set up payments banks. So, 1 is correct.</li>\n</ul>\n<p><strong>Statement 2:</strong> Scope of activities of Payment Banks as per RBI guidelines (we are mentioning only few of them):</p>\n<ul>\n<li>They can accept demand deposits.</li>\n<li>They can issue ATM/debit cards. Payments banks, however, cannot issue credit cards (as they can\u2019t lend money). So, 2 is wrong, which makes option B the only answer.</li>\n</ul>\n<p><strong>Statement 3:</strong> As per RBI guidelines, they cannot undertake lending activities.</p>\n<p><strong>Source</strong>: <a href=\"https://rbi.org.in/scripts/BS_PressReleaseDisplay.aspx?prid=32615\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">https://rbi.org.in/scripts/BS_PressReleaseDisplay.aspx?prid=32615</a></p>\n                                "}, {"question": "In the cities of our country, which among the following atmospheric gases are normally considered in calculating the value of Air Quality Index?\nCarbon dioxide\nCarbon monoxide\nNitrogen dioxide\nSulfur dioxide\nMethane\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below.", "options": ["(a) 1,2 and 3 only", "(b) 2, 3 and 4 only", "(c) 1, 4 and 5 only", "(d) 1,2, 3, 4 and 5"], "answer": "(b) 2, 3 and 4 only", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p><strong>Solution: B</strong></p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong>Only 2, 3 and 4 are correct.</p>\n<ul>\n<li>The Index was launched 2014 with outline&nbsp;<strong>\u2018One Number \u2013 One Color -One Description\u2019</strong>for the common man to judge the air quality within his vicinity.</li>\n<li><strong>The measurement of air quality is based on eight pollutants,&nbsp;</strong>namely: Particulate Matter (PM10), Particulate Matter (PM2.5), Nitrogen Dioxide (NO2), Sulphur Dioxide (SO2), Carbon Monoxide (CO), Ozone (O3), Ammonia (NH3), and Lead (Pb).</li>\n<li><strong>AQI has six categories of air quality.</strong>These are: Good, Satisfactory, Moderately Polluted, Poor, Very Poor and Severe.</li>\n<li>Air Quality Index doesn\u2019t include carbon dioxide and methane.</li>\n<li>It has been developed by&nbsp;<strong>the CPCB in consultation with IIT-Kanpur&nbsp;</strong>and an expert group comprising medical and air-quality professionals.</li>\n</ul>\n<p><strong>Source</strong>: <a href=\"http://www.hindustantimes.com/india/modi-launches-air-quality-index-wants-change-in-lifestyle-to-save-environment/story-C8VHWyZWYe36La6PQ7v2eO.html\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">http://www.hindustantimes.com/india/modi-launches-air-quality-index-wants-change-in-lifestyle-to-save-environment/story-C8VHWyZWYe36La6PQ7v2eO.html</a></p>\n                                "}, {"question": "Recently, which one of the following currencies has been proposed to be added to the basket of IMF\u2019s SDR?", "options": ["(a) Rouble", "(b) Rand", "(c) Indian Rupee", "(d) Renminbi"], "answer": "(d) Renminbi", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: D</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong>In the most recently concluded review (November 2015), the Executive Board of IMF decided that, effective October 1,2016, the Chinese renminbi (RMB) will be included in the SDR basket as a fifth currency, along with the U.S. dollar, euro, Japanese yen and pound sterling.</p>\n<p><strong>Source</strong>: <a href=\"https://www.imf.org/external/np/exr/facts/sdrcb.htm\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">https://www.imf.org/external/np/exr/facts/sdrcb.htm</a></p>\n                                "}, {"question": "Consider the following statements:\nThe Mangalyaan launched by ISRO\nis also called the Mars Orbiter Mission\nmade India the second country to have a spacecraft orbit the Mars after USA\nmade India the only country to be successful in making its spacecraft orbit the Mars in its very first attempt\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?", "options": ["a) 1 only", "(b) 2 and 3 only", "(c) 1 and 3 only", "d) 1,2 and 3"], "answer": "(c) 1 and 3 only", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: C</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong>Only 1 and 3 are correct.</p>\n<ul>\n<li>India is the only country to be successful in making its spacecraft orbit Mars in its very first attempt.</li>\n<li>India is the first Asian country and ISRO is the fourth space agency to send a satellite to Mars.</li>\n</ul>\n<p><strong>Source</strong>:</p>\n<ol>\n<li><a href=\"http://www.isro.gov.in/Spacecraft/mars-orbiter-mission-spacecraft\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">isro.gov.in/Spacecraft/mars-orbiter-mission-spacecraft</a></li>\n<li><a href=\"http://www.thehindu.com/opinion/op-ed/a-faster-cheaper-mars-orbiter/article6442854.ece\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">http://www.thehindu.com/opinion/op-ed/a-faster-cheaper-mars-orbiter/article6442ece</a></li>\n</ol>\n                                "}, {"question": "Consider the following statements:\nThe minimum age prescribed for any person to be a member of Panchayat is 25\nA Panchayat reconstituted after premature dissolution continues only for the remainder period.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?", "options": ["(a) 1 only", "(b) 2 only", "(c) Both 1 and 2", "(d) Neither 1 nor 2"], "answer": "(b) 2 only", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: B</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong>Only statement 2 is correct.</p>\n<ul>\n<li><u>Statement 1:</u> It is 21 years, so 1 is wrong.</li>\n<li><u>Statement 2:</u> A Panchayat reconstituted after premature dissolution (i.e., before the expiry of the full period of five years) shall continue only for the remainder of the period. But if the remainder of the period is less than six months it shall not be necessary to hold</li>\n</ul>\n<p><strong>Source</strong>: <a href=\"http://www.tn.gov.in/fsfc/Const%20Amend%2073.htm\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">http://www.tn.gov.in/fsfc/Const%20Amend%2073.htm</a></p>\n                                "}, {"question": "Satya Shodhak Samaj organized", "options": ["(a) a movement for upliftment of tribals in Bihar", "(b) a temple-entry movement in Gujarat", "(c) an anti-caste movement in Maharashtra", "(d) a peasant movement in Punjab"], "answer": "(c) an anti-caste movement in Maharashtra", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: C</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong>Clear answer. You can read more about the movement here</p>\n<p><a href=\"http://shodhganga.inflibnet.ac.in/bitstream/10603/20396/11/11_chapter%205.pdf\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">http://shodhganga.inflibnet.ac.in/bitstream/10603/20396/11/11_chapter%205.pdf</a></p>\n                                "}, {"question": "With reference to the cultural history of medieval India, consider the following statements :\nSiddhas (Sittars) of Tamil region were monotheistic and condemned idolatry.\nLingayats of Kannada region questioned the theory of rebirth and rejected the caste\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?", "options": ["(a) 1 only", "(b) 2 only", "(c) Both 1 and 2", "(d) Neither 1 nor 2"], "answer": "(c) Both 1 and 2", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: C</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong>Both the statements are correct.</p>\n<p><strong>Statement 1: </strong></p>\n<ul>\n<li>Siddhas believe in oneness of the transcendental being in the world as well as charity towards men. This clearly shows they believed there is only one God, i.e. monotheism.</li>\n<li>The Siddhar tradition has also been contrasted with the Bhakti tradition. Their attitude against idol worship and their stress on yoga, knowledge right conduct distinguished them from Bhakti cults. So, clearly 1 is correct.</li>\n</ul>\n<p><strong>Statement 2:</strong></p>\n<ul>\n<li>Basavanna (founder of Lingayatism) rebelled against the rigid practices of the caste system then prevalent in orthodox Hindu society and eventually began expounding his own philosophy with a casteless society at its core.</li>\n<li>Lingayats believed that there is no rebirth and on death the devotee reunites with Shiva never coming back to the World. So, 2 is also correct.</li>\n</ul>\n<p><strong>Source: </strong>Religion, Philosophy, Yoga: A Selection of Articles By Jean Filliozat<a href=\"http://tinyurl.com/gnbkxhs\">http://tinyurl.com/gnbkxhs</a></p>\n<p><a href=\"http://tinyurl.com/jophqme\">http://tinyurl.com/jophqme</a></p>\n<p><a href=\"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lingayatism\">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lingayatism</a></p>\n                                "}, {"question": "Recently, for the first time in our country, which of the following States has declared a particular butterfly as \u2018State Butterfly\u2019?", "options": ["(a) Arunachal Pradesh", "(b) Himachal Pradesh", "(c) Karnataka", "(d) Maharashtra"], "answer": "(d) Maharashtra", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: D</p>\n<p>Justification:</p>\n<p>\u00b7&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; In 2015, Maharashtra has become the first State in the country to have a \u2018State butterfly.\u2019</p>\n<p>\u00b7&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; The government&nbsp;declared the Blue Mormon (&nbsp;Papilio polymnestor) as the State butterfly. The decision was taken at a meeting of the State Wildlife Board</p>\n<p><a href=\"http://www.thehindu.com/news/national/other-states/maharashtra-gets-state-butterfly/article7342955.ece\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\"><strong>Source:</strong></a><a href=\"http://www.thehindu.com/news/national/other-states/maharashtra-\" rel=\"nofollow ugc\">http://www.thehindu.com/news/national/other-states/maharashtra-</a> gets-state-butterfly/article7342955.ece</p>\n                                "}, {"question": "Recently, which of the following States has explored the possibility of constructing an artificial inland port to be connected to sea by a long navigational channel?", "options": ["(a) Andhra Pradesh", "(b) Chhattisgarh", "(c) Karnataka", "(d) Rajasthan"], "answer": "(d) Rajasthan", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: D</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong></p>\n<ul>\n<li>A proposal received from Government of Rajasthan to develop Inland Shipping Port at Jalore which would be connected to the Arabian Sea by developing a channel along the Kutch Creek, was discussed by the officers of the Rajasthan Government with the officials of Inland Waterways Authority of India (IWAI).</li>\n<li>It was decided that a pre-feasibility study be undertaken by Government of Rajasthan containing all the technical parameters required to assess the possibility of developing the port at Jalore.</li>\n<li>IWAI has finalized the Terms of Reference for the study, which has been forwarded to Government of Rajasthan for necessary action.</li>\n</ul>\n<p><strong>Source</strong>: <a href=\"http://pib.nic.in/newsite/PrintRelease.aspx?relid=130196\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">http://pib.nic.in/newsite/PrintRelease.aspx?relid=130196</a></p>\n                                "}, {"question": "With reference to the International Monetary and Financial Committee (IMFC), consider the following statements :\nIMFC discusses matters of concern affecting the global economy, and advises the International Monetary Fund (IMF) on the direction of its work.\nThe World Bank participates as observer in IMFC\u2019s meetings.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?", "options": ["(a) 1 only", "(b) 2 only", "(c) Both 1 and 2", "(d) Neither 1 nor 2"], "answer": "(c) Both 1 and 2", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: C</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong>Both the statements are correct.</p>\n<p><strong>Statement 1:</strong> The IMFC advises and reports to the IMF Board of Governors on the supervision and management of the international monetary and financial system, including on responses to unfolding events that may disrupt the system.</p>\n<p><strong>Statement 2:</strong> A number of international institutions, including the World Bank, participate as observers in the IMFC\u2019s meetings.</p>\n<p><a href=\"http://www.imf.org/external/np/exr/facts/groups.htm\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">http://www.imf.org/external/np/exr/facts/groups.htm</a></p>\n                                "}, {"question": "With reference to \u2018Initiative for Nutritional Security through Intensive Millets Promotion\u2019, which of the following statements is/are correct?\nThis initiative aims to demonstrate the improved production and post-harvest technologies, and to demonstrate value addition techniques, in an integrated manner, with cluster approach.\nPoor, small, marginal and tribal farmers have larger stake in this scheme.\nAn important objective of the scheme is to encourage farmers of commercial crops to shift to millet cultivation by offering them free kits of critical inputs of nutrients and micro-irrigation equipment.\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below.", "options": ["(a) 1 only", "(b) 2 and 3 only", "(c) 1 and 2 only", "(d) 1, 2 and 3"], "answer": "(c) 1 and 2 only", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: C</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong>It was launched under the Rashtriya Krishi Vikas Yojana in 2011-12 for promotion of millets as Nutri-cereals.</p>\n<p><u>Statement 1:</u> It has been picked verbatim from the source mentioned below.</p>\n<p><u>Statement 2:</u> Certain districts with large crop area under millets but with productivity less than that of the National Average Yield could be taken up for active promotion of production technologies through block demonstrations.</p>\n<p>However, in case of small millets, which have low productivity in general and are taken by <strong>resource poor tribal farmers </strong>in remote interior areas, production programme would be organized in all the identified districts irrespective of their productivity levels.</p>\n<p>So, clearly 2 is correct.</p>\n<p><u>Statement</u> 3: The statement is partially wrong.</p>\n<p>We are posting verbatim \u2013 \u201cTechnology demonstration kits of critical inputs of nutrients and plant protection measures comprising of <strong>micro-nutrients (not micro-irrigation equipments)</strong>, fungicides and bio-fertilizers, DAP, urea, potash and pesticides including weedicides at a total cost of Rs. 3,000/- per ha for sorghum, pearl millet and finger millet and Rs. 2,000/- per ha for small millets would be supplied to all the farmers in the units.</p>\n<p>These kits would be supplied <strong>free of cost </strong>to the beneficiary farmers subject to maximum area of 2 hectare.</p>\n<p>So, 3 will actually be wrong, because even though the kits are given free of cost, it does not include micro-irrigation equipments.</p>\n<p><a href=\"http://agricoop.nic.in/Admin_Agricoop/Uploaded_File/INSIMP.pdf\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">http://agricoop.nic.in/Admin_Agricoop/Uploaded_File/INSIMP.pdf</a></p>\n                                "}, {"question": "Which of the following is/are the advantage /advantages of practising drip irrigation?\nReduction in weed\nReduction in soil salinity\nReduction in soil erosion\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below.", "options": ["(a) 1 and 2 only", "(b) 3 only", "(c) 1 and 3 only", "(d) None of the above is an advantage of practicing drip irrigation"], "answer": "(b) 3 only", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p></p><div id=\"wpwrap\">\n<div id=\"adminmenumain\" role=\"navigation\" aria-label=\"Main menu\">\n<p>Solution: C</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong>Only statement 1 and 3 are correct.</p>\n<p><u>Statement 1:</u> Weeds usually grow in between the plant rows due to availability of moisture on that strip of land. In drip irrigation, water is applied directly to the roots, and not the entire field (thus excluding the land space between plants where weeds usually grow). So, weed growth is inhibited.</p>\n<p><u>Statement 2:</u></p>\n<ul>\n<li>There may be some confusion in this statement. Generally excessive logging and flooded fields suffer from higher salinity. So, replacing conventional irrigation may help in curbing water-logged soil salinity.</li>\n<li>But, generally speaking, as a rule, we cannot claim that if drip irrigation system is installed on a farm land, it would always reduce soil salinity. Seen in isolation from instances of water logging (or other such cases), drip irrigation and soil salinity do not have much co-relation. The system simply delivers water to the roots of the plant.</li>\n<li>Also, if we use elimination, as 1 and 3 must be correct, there is no option \u201c1,2 and 3\u201d which automatically tells us that statement 2 is wrong.</li>\n</ul>\n<p><u>Statement</u> 3: Surface irrigation is a significant contributor to top soil erosion. Drip irrigation reduces soil erosion as water is delivered directly to plant roots at a very slow rate (unlike surface irrigation where water velocity can be fast).</p>\n<p><strong>Source</strong>:</p>\n<ol>\n<li><a href=\"https://www.irrigationdirect.com/articles/drip-irrigation-history-benefits\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">https://www.irrigationdirect.com/articles/drip-irrigation-history-benefits</a></li>\n<li><a href=\"http://www.agriinfo.in/default.aspx?page=topic&amp;superid=8&amp;topicid=2243\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">http://www.agriinfo.in/default.aspx?page=topic&amp;superid=8&amp;topicid=2243</a></li>\n</ol>\n</div>\n</div>\n<p></p>                                "}, {"question": "The term \u2018Base Erosion and Profit Shifting\u2019 is sometimes seen in the news in the context of", "options": ["(a) mining operation by multinational companies in resource-rich but backward areas", "(b) curbing of the tax evasion by multinational companies", "(c) exploitation of genetic resources of a country by multinational companies", "(d) lack of consideration of environmental costs in the planning and implementation of developmental projects"], "answer": "(b) curbing of the tax evasion by multinational companies", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: B</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong>Base erosion and profit shifting (BEPS) refers to tax avoidance strategies that exploit gaps and mismatches in tax rules to artificially shift profits to low or no-tax locations.</p>\n<p>Under the inclusive framework, over 100 countries and jurisdictions are collaborating to implement the BEPS measures and tackle BEPS.</p>\n<p>Double-tax avoidance treaties and tax-information exchange between member nations are used to curb this practice.</p>\n<p><a href=\"http://www.oecd.org/tax/beps/\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">http://www.oecd.org/tax/beps/</a></p>\n                                "}, {"question": "Consider the following pairs:\nFamous place                  Region \nBodhgaya                         Baghelkhand\nKhajuraho                        Bundelkhand\nShirdi                                   Vidarbha\nNasik (Nashik)                    Malwa\nTirupati                             Rayalaseema\nWhich of the pairs given above are correctly matched?", "options": ["(a) 1, 2 and 4", "(b) 2, 3, 4 and 5", "(c) 2 and 5 only", "(d) 1, 3, 4 and 5"], "answer": "(c) 2 and 5 only", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p></p><h1>Solution: C</h1>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong>Only 2 and 5 are correctly matched.</p>\n<ul>\n<li>Baghelkhand is in Central India, whereas Bodhgaya is in Bihar. So, if 1is wrong, we have options (b) and (c) remaining.</li>\n<li>Malwa doesn\u2019t extend to Nasik and Shirdi is in Ahmadnagar (far from Vidarbha). So, 3 and 4 are wrong.</li>\n</ul>\n<p>The only answer can be C.</p>\n<p><strong>Source: </strong>Map-based questions on important regions</p>\n<p></p>                                "}, {"question": "In the context of the history of India, consider the following pairs:\nTerm                                               Description\nEripatti          : Land, revenue from which was set apart for the maintenance of the village tank\nTaniyurs        : Villages donated to a single Brahmin or a group of Brahmins\nGhatikas        : Colleges generally attached to the temples\nWhich of the pairs given above is/are correctly matched?", "options": ["(a) 1 and 2", "(b) 3 only", "(c) 2 and 3", "(d) 1 and 3"], "answer": "(d) 1 and 3", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: D</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong>Only 1 and 3 are correctly matched.</p>\n<ul>\n<li><u>Statement 1:</u> A special category of land Eripatti or tank land, was known only in south India, This was land donated by individuals, the revenue from which was set apart for the maintenance of\u2019 the village tank, which indicates the dependence of the village on the tank for irrigation.</li>\n<li><u>Statement 2: </u>Taniyurs were distinct revenue units under Cholas.</li>\n<li><u>Statement</u> 3: In South India centres of higher learning were known as Ghatikas. There was a famous Ghatika at Kanchi, drawing students from far and near. These Ghatikas were run in temples.</li>\n</ul>\n                                "}, {"question": "Regarding \u2018Atal Pension Yojana\u2019, which of the following statements is/are correct?\nIt is a minimum guaranteed pension scheme mainly targeted at unorganized sector workers.\nOnly one member of a family can join the scheme.\nSame amount of pension is guaranteed for the spouse for life after subscriber\u2019s death.\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below.", "options": ["(a) 1 only", "(b) 2 and 3 only", "(c) 1 and 3 only", "(d) 1,2 and 3"], "answer": "(c) 1 and 3 only", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: C</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong>Only 1 and 3 are correct.</p>\n<p><strong>Statement 1:</strong> The Yojana mainly addresses the longevity risks among the workers in unorganized sector and encourages them to voluntarily save for their retirement. So, 1 is correct.</p>\n<p><strong>Statement 2:</strong> Atal Pension Yojana (APY) is open to all bank account holders who are not members of any statutory social security scheme. So, 2 is wrong.</p>\n<p><strong>Statement 3</strong>: As per the Ministry of Finance, \u201cThe spouse of the subscriber shall be entitled to receive the same pension amount as that of the subscriber until the death of the spouse. After the death of both the subscriber and the spouse, the nominee of the subscriber shall be entitled to receive the pension wealth, as accumulated till age of 60 years of the subscribe\u201d. So, clearly 3 is correct.</p>\n<p><strong>Source</strong>:</p>\n<ol>\n<li><a href=\"http://pib.nic.in/newsite/PrintRelease.aspx?relid=116208\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\"><u>htt</u><u>p://pib.nic.in/newsite/PrintRelease.aspx?relid=116208</u></a></li>\n<li>Some recent changes (on which statement 3 is based): <a href=\"http://economictimes.indiatimes.com/wealth/plan/government-amends-atal-pension-yojana/articleshow/51511223.cms\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\"><u>htt</u><u>p://economictimes.indiatimes.com/wealth/plan/government-amends-atal-pension-</u><u>yojana/articleshow/5151122cms</u></a></li>\n</ol>\n                                "}, {"question": "What is/are the importance/importances of the \u2018United Nations Convention to Combat Desertification\u2019?\nIt aims to promote effective action through innovative national programmesand supportive inter-national partnerships.\nIt has a special/particular focus on South Asia and North Africa regions, and its Secretariat facilitates the allocation of major portion of financial resources to these\nIt is committed to bottom-up approach, encouraging the participation of local people in combating the desertification.\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below.", "options": ["(a) 1 only", "(b) 2 and 3 only", "(c) 1 and 3 only", "(d) 1,2 and 3"], "answer": "(c) 1 and 3 only", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p></p><div id=\"wpwrap\">\n<div id=\"adminmenumain\" role=\"navigation\" aria-label=\"Main menu\">\n<h1></h1>\n<p>Solution: C</p>\n<p>Justification: Statement 1 and 3 are only correct.</p>\n<p><strong>Statement 1 and 2:</strong> Please see the Q Source.</p>\n<p><strong>Statement 2: </strong></p>\n<ul>\n<li>Though desertification affects Africa the most, where two-thirds of the continent is desert or drylands, it is not a problem confined to drylands in Africa. United States, Latin America and the Caribbean have a high percentage of degraded lands.</li>\n<li>The problem is starker in developing countries (majority of population in drylands is living in these countries). So, the UNCCD secretariat facilitates south-south cooperation is addressing desertification.</li>\n<li>We could not find any such provision that the UNCCD secretariat allocates majority of resources to the South Asian and North African regions, even though it focuses on these regions.</li>\n</ul>\n<p><strong>Source:</strong></p>\n<ol>\n<li><a href=\"http://www.unccd.int/en/about-the-convention/Pages/About-the-Convention.aspx\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">http://www.unccd.int/en/about-the-convention/Pages/About-the-Convention.aspx</a></li>\n<li><a href=\"http://www.unesco.org/mab/doc/ekocd/chapter14.html\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">http://www.unesco.org/mab/doc/ekocd/chapter1html</a></li>\n<li><a href=\"http://www.unccd.int/en/resources/Library/Pages/FAQ.aspx\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">http://www.unccd.int/en/resources/Library/Pages/FAQ.aspx</a></li>\n</ol>\n</div>\n</div>\n<p></p>                                "}, {"question": "What is/are the purpose/purposes of Government\u2019s \u2018Sovereign Gold Bond Scheme\u2019 and \u2018Gold Monetization Scheme\u2019?\nTo bring the idle gold lying with Indian households into the economy\nTo promote FDI in the gold and jewellery sector\nTo reduce India\u2019s dependence on gold imports Select the correct answer using the code given below.", "options": ["(a) 1 only", "(b) 2 and 3 only", "(c) 1 and 3 only", "(d) 1, 2 and 3"], "answer": "(c) 1 and 3 only", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: C</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong>The scheme doesn\u2019t intend to bring FDI in gold and jewellery sector, and by eliminating this only possible answers you have are either A or C.</p>\n<p>Both schemes aim at reducing physical demand of gold and thus bring down gold imports which clearly tell us that the answer must be C.</p>\n<p><a href=\"http://www.financialexpress.com/markets/commodities/gold-monetisation-scheme-gold-monetization-scheme-indian-gold-coin-launched-2015/161906/\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\"></a><a href=\"http://www.financialexpress.com/markets/commodities/gold-monetisation-scheme-\" rel=\"nofollow ugc\">http://www.financialexpress.com/markets/commodities/gold-monetisation-scheme-</a> gold-monetization-scheme-indian-gold-coin-launched-2015/161906/</p>\n                                "}, {"question": "Which of the following statements is/are correct?\nViruses can infect\nbacteria\nfungi\nplants\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below.", "options": ["(a) 1 and 2 only", "(b) 3 only", "(c) 1 and 3 only", "(d) 1, 2 and 3"], "answer": "(d) 1, 2 and 3", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: D</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong>Viruses are known to infect almost any kind of host that has living cells. Animals, plants, fungi, and bacteria are all subject to viral infection.</p>\n<p>A bacteriophage is a virus that infects and replicates within a bacterium. Mycoviruses are viruses that infect fungi. A host of other Viruses affect plants.</p>\n<p><a href=\"http://www.peteducation.com/article.cfm?c=16%2B2160&amp;aid=2956\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">http://www.peteducation.com/article.cfm?c=16+2160&amp;aid=2956</a></p>\n                                "}, {"question": "On which of the following can you find the Bureau of Energy Efficiency Star Label?\nCeiling fans\nElectric geysers\nTubular fluorescent lamps\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below.", "options": ["(a) 1 and 2 only", "(b) 3 only", "(c) 2 and 3 only", "(d) 1,2 and 3"], "answer": "(d) 1,2 and 3", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: D</p>\n<p>Justification: All are correct.</p>\n<p><a href=\"https://beestarlabel.com/\"><strong>The Standards &amp; Labeling Programme </strong></a>&nbsp;is one of the major thrust areas of BEE. A key objective of this scheme is to provide the consumer an informed choice about the energy saving and thereby the cost saving potential of the relevant marketed product. The scheme targets display of energy performance labels on high energy end use equipment &amp; appliances and lays down minimum energy performance standards.</p>\n<p>The appliances covered under the programme are given below:</p>\n<p><a href=\"http://www.beepindia.org/sites/default/files/Chapter%206%20-%20Appliances.pdf\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\"><strong>Source:</strong></a><a href=\"http://www.beepindia.org/sites/default/files/Chapter%206%20-\" rel=\"nofollow ugc\">http://www.beepindia.org/sites/default/files/Chapter%206%20-</a></p>\n<p><a href=\"http://www.beepindia.org/sites/default/files/Chapter%206%20-%20Appliances.pdf\">%20Appliances.pdf</a></p>\n                                "}, {"question": "Consider the following :\nCalcutta Unitarian Committee\nTabernacle of New Dispensation\nIndian Reform Association\nKeshab Chandra Sen is associated with the establishment of which of the above?", "options": ["(a) 1 and 3 only", "(b) 2 and 3 only", "(c) 3 only", "(d) 1, 2 and 3"], "answer": "(b) 2 and 3 only", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: B</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong>Calcutta Unitarian Committee was established in 1823 by Rammohun Roy, Dwarkanath Tagore, and William Adam. So, 1 is wrong.</p>\n<p>In 1868, Keshub laid the foundation stone of his new church, the Tabernacle of New Dispensation. So, 2 is correct.</p>\n<p>Indian reform association was founded in 1870 with Keshub Chunder Sen as president. It represented the secular side of the Brahmo Samaj and included many who did not belong to the Brahmo Samaj. So, 3 is correct.</p>\n<p><a href=\"http://www.thebrahmosamaj.net/founders/keshub.html\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">http://www.thebrahmosamaj.net/founders/keshub.html</a></p>\n<p><a href=\"http://www.thebrahmosamaj.net/history/chronology.html\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">http://www.thebrahmosamaj.net/history/chronology.html</a></p>\n                                "}, {"question": "The Parliament of India acquires the power to legislate on any item in the State List in the national interest if a resolution to that effect is passed by the", "options": ["(a) LokSabha by a simple majority of its total membership", "(b) LokSabha by a majority of not less than two-thirds of its total membership", "(c) Rajya Sabha by a simple majority of its total membership", "(d) Rajya Sabha by a majority of not less than two-thirds of its members present and voting"], "answer": "(d) Rajya Sabha by a majority of not less than two-thirds of its members present and voting", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: D</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong>If Rajya Sabha approves a resolution with special majority and declares that a subject is of national interest, the Parliament can make a law on the particular subject in the state list (7<sup>th</sup> Schedule).</p>\n<p><strong>Source: </strong>Indian Polity: M Laxmikanth</p>\n                                "}, {"question": "With reference to the Agreement at the UNFCCC Meeting in Paris in 2015, which of the following statements is/are correct?\nThe Agreement was signed by all the member countries of the UN and it will go into effect in\nThe Agreement aims to limit the greenhouse gas emissions so that the rise in average global temperature by the end of this century does not exceed 2 \u00b0C oreven 1.5 \u00b0C above pre-industrial levels.\nDeveloped countries acknowledged their historical responsibility in global warming and committed to donate $ 1000 billion a year from 2020 to help developing countries to cope with climate change.\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below.", "options": ["(a) 1 and 3 only", "(b) 2 only", "(c) 2 and 3 only", "(d) 1,2 and 3"], "answer": "(b) 2 only", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: B</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong>Only statement 2 is correct.</p>\n<ul>\n<li><u>Statement 1:</u> It was only \u201cagreed\u201d by 195 nations in Paris at the conference. The agreement will enter into force only after 55 countries that account for at least 55% of global emissions have deposited their instruments of ratification. So, 1 is wrong.</li>\n<li><u>Statement</u> 3<u>:</u> Developed countries will work to define a clear roadmap on ratcheting up climate finance to USD 100 billion (not USD 1000 billion) by So, 3 is wrong.</li>\n</ul>\n<p>The only answer can be option B.</p>\n<p><strong>Source</strong>: <a href=\"http://newsroom.unfccc.int/unfccc-newsroom/finale-cop21/\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">http://newsroom.unfccc.int/unfccc-newsroom/finale-cop21/</a></p>\n                                "}, {"question": "Pradhan Mantri MUDRA Yojana is aimed at", "options": ["(a) bringing the small entrepreneurs into formal financial system", "(b) providing loans to poor farmers for cultivating particular crops", "(c) providing pensions to old and destitute persons", "(d) funding the voluntary organizations involved in the promotion of skill development and employment generation"], "answer": "(a) bringing the small entrepreneurs into formal financial system", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p></p><div id=\"wpwrap\">\n<div id=\"adminmenumain\" role=\"navigation\" aria-label=\"Main menu\">\n<p>Solution: A</p>\n<p><a href=\"http://www.icicibank.com/Personal-Banking/loans/pradhan-mantri-mudra-yojana.page\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\"><strong>Justification: </strong></a><a href=\"http://www.icicibank.com/Personal-Banking/loans/pradhan-mantri-\" rel=\"nofollow ugc\">http://www.icicibank.com/Personal-Banking/loans/pradhan-mantri-</a> mudra-yojana.page</p>\n</div>\n</div>\n<p></p>                                "}, {"question": "What is/are common to the two historical places known as Ajanta and Mahabalipuram?\nBoth were built in the same period.\nBoth belong to the same religious denomination.\nBoth have rock-cut monuments.\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below.", "options": ["(a) 1 and 2 only", "(b) 3 only", "(c) 1 and 3 only", "(d) None of the statements given above is correct"], "answer": "(b) 3 only", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: B</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong><u>Statement 1:</u> As per ASI Website, \u201cWhile there is some evidence of architectural activity going back to the period of Mahendravarman-I (AD 600-30), the father of Mamalla, most of the monuments are attributed to the period of Narasimhavarman-I Mamalla (AD 630-68) \u2013 the Pallava ruler.</p>\n<p>On the other hand Ajanta caves were excavated in different periods (circa. 2nd century B.C. to 6th century A.D.) according to the necessity. So, clearly 1 is wrong.</p>\n<p><u>Statement 2:</u> Mahabalipuram contains rock-cut rathas, sculptured scenes on open rocks like Arjuna\u2019s penance, the caves of Govardhanadhari and Mahishasuramardini, the Jala- Sayana Perumal temple (the sleeping Mahavishnu or Chakrin at the rear part of the Shore temple complex). So, it is more linked to the Vaishnavites.</p>\n<p>On the other hand, Ajanta is linked more to the Buddhist religious denomination.</p>\n<p>Statement 2 is also wrong.</p>\n<p><u>Statement</u> 3: Both have rock-cut monuments, because cave cut Chaityas, Viharas and Stupas can be clearly seen at Ajanta. Also, the mural paintings that are made at Ajanta involve some rock-cutting as per ASI.</p>\n<p>Mahabalipuram is famous for rock monuments as described above. Only 3 is correct.</p>\n<p><a href=\"http://asi.nic.in/asi_monu_whs_mahabalipuram.asp\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">http://asi.nic.in/asi_monu_whs_mahabalipuram.asp</a></p>\n<p><a href=\"http://asi.nic.in/asi_monu_whs_ajanta.asp\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">http://asi.nic.in/asi_monu_whs_ajanta.asp</a></p>\n                                "}, {"question": "With reference to an initiative called \u2018The Economics of Ecosystems and Biodiversity (TEEB)\u2019, which of the following statements is/are correct?\nIt is an initiative hosted by UNEP, IMF and World Economic Forum.\nIt is a global initiative that focuses on drawing attention to the economic benefits of\nIt presents an approach that can help decision-makers recognize, demonstrate and capture the value of ecosystems and biodiversity.\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below.", "options": ["(a) 1 and 2 only", "(b) 3 only", "(c) 2 and 3 only", "(d) 1, 2 and 3"], "answer": "(c) 2 and 3 only", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: C</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong><u>Statement 1:</u> The founding of TEER is actually a bit elaborate. It started from the G8+5 environment ministers since 2007. You can read more about it in the source given below.</p>\n<p>The TEEB office is hosted by the United Nations Environment Programme (UNEP).</p>\n<p><u>Statement 2 and</u> 3: Lifted nearly verbatim from the source below.</p>\n<p><a href=\"http://www.teebweb.org/about/the-initiative/\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">http://www.teebweb.org/about/the-initiative/</a></p>\n                                "}, {"question": "With reference to \u2018Red Sanders\u2019, sometimes seen in the news, consider the following statements:\nIt is a tree species found in a part of South India.\nIt is one of the most important trees in the tropical rain forest areas of South India.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?", "options": ["(a) 1 only", "(b) 2 only", "(c) Both 1 and 2", "(d) Neither 1 nor 2"], "answer": "(a) 1 only", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p></p><div id=\"wpwrap\">\n<div id=\"adminmenumain\" role=\"navigation\" aria-label=\"Main menu\">\n<p>Solution: A</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong><u>Statement 1:</u> Red Sanders (a tree) has a highly restrictive distribution in the South Eastern portion of Indian peninsula (Eastern Ghats of South India) to which it is endemic. So, clearly 1 is correct.</p>\n<p><u>Statement 2:</u> It occurs in the forest formation which is classified as \u201cSouthern Tropical Dry Deciduous Forests\u201d. So, clearly 2 is wrong.</p>\n<p>It is generally found at altitudes of 150 \u2013 900 m. It grows on dry, hilly, often rocky ground, and occasionally found on precipitous hill sides also. It prefers lateritic and gravelly soil and cannot tolerate water logging.</p>\n<p><a href=\"http://www.moef.nic.in/downloads/public-information/Chap-8-new.pdf\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">http://www.moef.nic.in/downloads/public-information/Chap-8-new.pdf</a></p>\n<p><a href=\"http://www.thehindu.com/news/national/andhra-pradesh/international-red-sanders-smuggler-nabbed/article8813238.ece\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\"></a><a href=\"http://www.thehindu.com/news/national/andhra-pradesh/international-red-sanders-\" rel=\"nofollow ugc\">http://www.thehindu.com/news/national/andhra-pradesh/international-red-sanders-</a> smuggler-nabbed/article8813238.ece</p>\n</div>\n</div>\n<p></p>                                "}, {"question": "With reference to the cultural history of India, the memorizing of chronicles, dynastic histories and Epic tales was the profession of who of the following?", "options": ["(a) Shramana", "(b) Parivraajaka", "(c) Agrahaarika", "(d) Maagadha"], "answer": "(d) Maagadha", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: D</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong>Excerpts from Romila Thapar, Ancient India, \u201cThe memorizing of chronicles, dynastic histories, or epic tales was the work of a group of people, the sutas and magadhas.\u201d</p>\n<p><strong>Source</strong>: <a href=\"http://tinyurl.com/hb6mepk\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">http://tinyurl.com/hb6mepk</a></p>\n                                "}, {"question": "\u2018Belt and Road Initiative\u2019 is sometimes mentioned in the news in the context of the affairs of", "options": ["(a) African Union", "(b) Brazil", "(c) European Union", "(d) China"], "answer": "(d) China", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: D</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong><a href=\"http://thediplomat.com/tag/one-belt-one-road/\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">http://thediplomat.com/tag/one-belt-one-road/</a></p>\n                                "}, {"question": "Which of the following is/are tributary/tributaries of Brahmaputra?\nDibang\nKameng\nLohit\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below.", "options": ["(a) 1 only", "(b) 2 and 3 only", "(c) 1 and 3 only", "(d) 1, 2 and 3"], "answer": "(d) 1, 2 and 3", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: D</p>\n<p><a href=\"http://www.india-wris.nrsc.gov.in/wrpinfo/index.php?title=Brahmaputra\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\"><strong>Justification: </strong></a><a href=\"http://www.india-wris.nrsc.gov.in/wrpinfo/index.php\" rel=\"nofollow ugc\">http://www.india-wris.nrsc.gov.in/wrpinfo/index.php</a>? title=Brahmaputra</p>\n                                "}, {"question": "Why does the Government of India promote the use of Neem-coated Urea\u2019 in agriculture?", "options": ["(a) Release of Neem oil in the soil increases nitrogen fixation by the soil microorganisms", "(b) Neem coating slows down the rate of dissolution of urea in the soil", "(c) Nitrous oxide, which is a greenhouse gas, is not at all released into atmosphere by crop fields", "(d) It is a combination of a weedicide and a fertilizer for particular crops"], "answer": "(b) Neem coating slows down the rate of dissolution of urea in the soil", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: B</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong></p>\n<p>Down-to-earth explains the role of Neem-coated Urea very well. We are posting from it.</p>\n<ul>\n<li>\u201cUrea is an important supplier of nitrogen, which is necessary for the development of plants. But only 30-40 per cent of nitrogen present in the urea is utilised by The rest gets degraded in various stages.</li>\n<li>When ordinary urea is applied, it gets converted to ammonium carbamate. Some of this gets converted to ammonia gas in what is called ammonia volatilisation. About 8-10 per cent nitrogen is lost during volatilisation.</li>\n<li>The rest of the ammonium carbamate undergoes chemical transfor-mation and nitrates are formed. Some of these are absorbed by the plants.</li>\n<li>The rest are either leached into the underground water or are denitrified to gaseous nitrogen and nitrous oxide under anaerobic conditions (absence of oxygen).</li>\n<li>Neem has properties that check nitrogen loss at each stage. It slows down the process of nitrate formation and hence excess nitrate is not available for denitrification.</li>\n<li>So, clearly B is the most appropriate option. Neem coating also prevents Urea from being diverted to non-agricultural purposes.</li>\n</ul>\n<p><strong>Source</strong>: <a href=\"http://www.downtoearth.org.in/news/urea-coated-with-neem-12520\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">http://www.downtoearth.org.in/news/urea-coated-with-neem-12520</a></p>\n                                "}, {"question": "The term \u2018Intended Nationally Determined Contributions\u2019 is sometimes seen in the news in the context of", "options": ["(a) pledges made by the European countries to rehabilitate refugees from the war-affected Middle East", "(b) plan of action outlined by the countries of the world to combat climate change", "(c) capital contributed by the member countries in the establishment of Asian Infrastructure Investment Bank", "(d) plan of action outlined by the countries of the world regarding Sustainable Development Goals"], "answer": "(b) plan of action outlined by the countries of the world to combat climate change", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: B</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: Nationally determined contributions</strong>&nbsp;(<strong>NDCs</strong>) are at the heart of the Paris Agreement and the achievement of&nbsp;<strong>these</strong>&nbsp;long-term goals.&nbsp;<strong>NDCs</strong>&nbsp;embody efforts by each country to reduce&nbsp;<strong>national</strong>&nbsp;emissions and adapt to the impacts of climate change.</p>\n<p><strong>Source</strong>: <a href=\"http://unfccc.int/focus/indc_portal/items/8766.php\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">http://unfccc.int/focus/indc_portal/items/8766.php</a></p>\n                                "}, {"question": "Which of the following is/are the indicator/indicators used by IFPRI to compute the Global Hunger Index Report?\nUndernourishment\nChild stunting\nChild mortality\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below.", "options": ["a) 1 only", "(b) 2 and 3 only", "(c) 1,2 and 3", "(d) 1 and 3 only"], "answer": "(c) 1,2 and 3", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: C</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong>All three are correct.</p>\n<p>To reflect the multidimensional nature of hunger, the GHI combines the following four component indicators into one index:</p>\n<ol>\n<li><strong>Undernourishment</strong>: the proportion of undernourished people as a percentage of the population (reflecting the share of the population whose caloric intake is insufficient;</li>\n<li><strong>Child wasting</strong>: the proportion of children under the age of five who suffer from wasting (that is, low weight for their height, reflecting acute under-nutrition);</li>\n<li><strong>Child stunting</strong>: the proportion of children under the age of five who suffer from stunting (that is, low height for their age, reflecting chronic under-nutrition); and Child mortality: the mortality rate of children under the age of five (partially reflecting the fatal synergy of inadequate nutrition and unhealthy environments).</li>\n</ol>\n<p><strong>Source</strong>: <a href=\"http://www.ifpri.org/topic/global-hunger-index\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">http://www.ifpri.org/topic/global-hunger-index</a></p>\n                                "}, {"question": "Recently, linking of which of the following rivers was undertaken?", "options": ["(a) Cauvery and Tungabhadra", "(b) Godavari and Krishna", "(c) Mahanadi and Sone", "(d) Narmada and Tapti"], "answer": "(b) Godavari and Krishna", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: B</p>\n<p>Justification: In September 2015, after flowing 124 km, water from the Godavari river in Andhra Pradesh reached the Krishna delta region, marking a milestone in the river-interlinking project.</p>\n<p><a href=\"//indianexpress.com/article/explained/godavari-and-krishna-rivers-interlink-when-two-rivers-meet/\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\"><strong>Source: </strong></a><a href=\"http://indianexpress.com/article/explained/godavari-and-krishna-rivers-interlink-when-two-rivers-meet/\" rel=\"nofollow ugc\">http://indianexpress.com/article/explained/godavari-and-krishna-rivers-interlink-when-two-rivers-meet/</a></p>\n                                "}, {"question": "Consider the following statements:\nThe Sustainable Development Goals were first proposed in 1972 by a global think tank called the \u2018Club of Rome\u2019.\nThe Sustainable Development Goals have to be achieved by\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?", "options": ["a) 1 only", "b) 2 only", "c) Both 1 and 2", "d) Neither 1 nor 2"], "answer": "b) 2 only", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: B</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong>Only statement 2 is correct.</p>\n<p><u>Statement 1:</u> The first report of the Club of Rome was the famous \u201cThe limits to growth\u201d thesis brought out in 1972.</p>\n<ul>\n<li>While the report did talk about the need of reducing our consumption habits and sustainable development, it is hard to conclude that the SDGs were first proposed by them.</li>\n<li>This is because SDGs are a comprehensive set of goals that include not only environmental conservation, but also reducing poverty, ensuring education, curbing malnutrition and hunger etc. So, we believe 1 should be wrong.</li>\n</ul>\n<p><u>Statement 2:</u> It is officially known as \u201cTransforming our world: the 2030 Agenda for Sustainable Development\u201d</p>\n<p><strong>Source</strong>: <a href=\"http://donellameadows.org/archives/the-club-of-rome-and-sustainable-development/\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">http://donellameadows.org/archives/the-club-of-rome-and-sustainable-development/</a></p>\n                                "}, {"question": "A recent movie titled The Man Who Knew Infinity is based on the biography of", "options": ["(a) S. Ramanujan", "(b) S. Chandrasekhar", "(c) S. N. Bose", "(d) C. V. Raman"], "answer": "(a) S. Ramanujan", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p></p><h1>Solution: A</h1>\n<p><strong>Justification:</strong></p>\n<ul>\n<li>It is a 2015 British biographical drama film based on the 1991 book of the same name by Robert Kanigel.</li>\n<li>The film stars Dev Patel as the real-life Srinivasa Ramanujan, a mathematician who after growing up poor in Madras, India, earns admittance to Cambridge University during World War I, where he becomes a pioneer in mathematical theories.</li>\n<li>Distinguished mathematicians Manjul Bhargava and Ken Ono are Associate Producers of the film.</li>\n</ul>\n<p></p>                                "}, {"question": "In the context of the developments in Bioinformatics, the term \u2018transcriptome\u2019, sometimes seen in the news, refers to", "options": ["(a) a range of enzymes used in genome editing", "(b) the full range of mRNA molecules expressed by an organism", "(c) the description of the mechanism of gene expression", "(d) a mechanism of genetic mutations taking place in cells"], "answer": "(b) the full range of mRNA molecules expressed by an organism", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: B</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong>A transcriptome is the full range of messenger RNA, or mRNA, molecules expressed by an organism.</p>\n<p>The term \u201ctranscriptome\u201d can also be used to describe the array of mRNA transcripts produced in a particular cell or tissue type.</p>\n<p>In contrast with the genome, which is characterized by its stability, the transcriptome actively changes.</p>\n<p>In fact, an organism\u2019s transcriptome varies depending on many factors, including stage of development and environmental conditions.</p>\n<p><a href=\"http://www.nature.com/scitable/definition/transcriptome-296\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">http://www.nature.com/scitable/definition/transcriptome-296</a></p>\n                                "}, {"question": "In the context of which of the following do you sometimes find the terms `amber box, blue box and green box\u2019 in the news?", "options": ["(a) WTO affairs", "(b) SAARC affairs", "(c) UNFCCC affairs", "(d) India-EU negotiations on FTA"], "answer": "(a) WTO affairs", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: A</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong>They relate to direct/indirect support given by states to their industries and agriculture, and regulate such supports as they have a bearing on international trade.</p>\n<p><strong>Source: </strong>WTO Website</p>\n                                "}, {"question": "Consider the following statements:\nThe Chief Secretary in a State is appointed by the Governor of that State.\nThe Chief Secretary in a State has a fixed tenure.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?", "options": ["(a) 1 only", "(b) 2 only", "(c) Both 1 and 2", "(d) Neither 1 nor 2"], "answer": "(d) Neither 1 nor 2", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: D</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong>Both the statements are wrong.</p>\n<p><strong>Statement 1</strong>: Chief Secretary (CS) is chosen by Chief Minister from among the senior most IAS officers. Hence, statement 1 is incorrect.</p>\n<p><strong>Statement 2:</strong> There is <strong>no </strong>fixed tenure for the post of Chief Secretary. In this context, the Administrative Reforms Commission, in its report on State Administration in 1969, had recommended that a Chief Secretary should have a minimum tenure of three to four years.</p>\n<p><strong>Source: </strong>Indian Public Administration: Institutions and Issues <a href=\"http://tinyurl.com/hozxoma\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">http://tinyurl.com/hozxoma</a></p>\n                                "}, {"question": "Which of the following best describes/ describe the aim of \u2018Green India Mission\u2019 of the Government of India?\nIncorporating environmental benefits and costs into the Union and State Budgets thereby implementing the `green accounting\u2019\nLaunching the second green revolution to enhance agricultural output so as to ensure food security to one and all in the future\nRestoring and enhancing forest cover and responding to climate change by a combination of adaptation and mitigation measures\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below.", "options": ["(a) 1 only", "(b) 2 and 3 only", "(c) 3 only", "(d) 1, 2 and 3"], "answer": "(c) 3 only", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p></p><div id=\"wpwrap\">\n<div id=\"adminmenumain\" role=\"navigation\" aria-label=\"Main menu\">\n<p>Solution: C</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong>The mission intends to increase forest/tree cover; improve/enhance eco- system services and to increase forest based livelihood income of about 3 million households. So, rest other statements (other than 3) are thus wrong.</p>\n<p><a href=\"http://www.envfor.nic.in/major-initiatives/national-mission-green-india-gim\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">http://www.envfor.nic.in/major-initiatives/national-mission-green-india-gim</a></p>\n</div>\n</div>\n<p></p>                                "}, {"question": "With reference to \u2018stand up India scheme\u2019, which of the following statement is/are correct?\nIts purpose is to promote entrepreneurship among SC/ST and women\nIt provides for refinance through SIDBI.\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below.", "options": ["a) 1 only", "(b) 2 only", "(c) Both 1 and 2", "(d) Neither 1 nor 2"], "answer": "(c) Both 1 and 2", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: C</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong>Straight forward question.</p>\n<p>The scheme promotes entrepreneurship among SC/ST and Women entrepreneurs, and facilitates at least two such projects per bank branch.</p>\n<p>The Stand Up India Scheme provides for refinance window through Small Industries Development Bank of India (SIDBI) with an initial amount of Rs. 10,000 crore. So, 2 is correct.</p>\n<p><a href=\"http://pib.nic.in/newsite/PrintRelease.aspx?relid=134220\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">http://pib.nic.in/newsite/PrintRelease.aspx?relid=134220</a></p>\n                                "}, {"question": "With reference to `IFC Masala Bonds\u2019, sometimes seen in the news, which of the statements given below is/are correct?\nThe International Finance Corporation, which offers these bonds, is an arm of the World Bank.\nThey are the rupee-denominated bonds and are a source of debt financing for the public and private sector.\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below.", "options": ["(a) 1 only", "(b) 2 only", "(c) Both 1 and 2", "(d) Neither 1 nor 2"], "answer": "(c) Both 1 and 2", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: C</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong>Both the statements are correct.</p>\n<p><strong>Statement 1: </strong></p>\n<ul>\n<li>The World Bank Group (WBG) consists of five organizations \u2013 IBRD, IDA, IFC, MIGA and ICSID.</li>\n<li>IFC is a member of the World Bank Group (WBG) and at the same time it\u2019s called as the <strong>World Bank\u2019s private sector lending arm</strong>with a stated objective to ensure that any financing does not result in harm to communities and the environment. (<strong>Source</strong>: <a href=\"https://www.oxfam.org/en/pressroom/pressreleases/2013-02-08/world-banks-private-sector-financing-arm-doesnt-know\">https://www.oxfam.org/en/pressroom/pressreleases/2013-02-08/world-banks-private-sector-financing-arm-doesnt-know</a>)</li>\n<li><strong>Another source that mentions IFC as WB\u2019s arm</strong>\u2013 <a href=\"https://www.icij.org/blog/2015/06/numbers-world-banks-lesser-known-arm-ifc\">https://www.icij.org/blog/2015/06/numbers-world-banks-lesser-known-arm-ifc</a>(read first paragraph)</li>\n<li><a href=\"https://www.theguardian.com/global-development/2016/mar/30/world-bank-lending-arm-ifc-sees-off-lawsuit-by-indian-fishermen-power-plant\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\"><strong>Another source</strong>: </a><a href=\"https://www.theguardian.com/global-development/2016/mar/30/world-bank-lending-arm-ifc-sees-off-lawsuit-by-indian-fishermen-power-plant\" rel=\"nofollow ugc\">https://www.theguardian.com/global-development/2016/mar/30/world-bank-lending-arm-ifc-sees-off-lawsuit-by-indian-fishermen-power-plant</a></li>\n</ul>\n<p><strong>Statement 2</strong><u>:</u> IFC has been issuing offshore rupee bonds known as \u2018Masala Bonds\u2019. They provide a new source of funding for Indian companies which benefit in the longer term from comparative pricing of bonds.</p>\n<p><strong>Source</strong>:</p>\n<ol>\n<li><a href=\"http://economictimes.indiatimes.com/markets/bonds/masala-bonds-can-be-new-funding-source-for-indian-cos-ifc/articleshow/51762984.cms\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">http://economictimes.indiatimes.com/markets/bonds/masala-bonds-can-be-new-funding-source-for-indian-cos-ifc/articleshow/51762cms</a></li>\n</ol>\n<p><a href=\"http://www.ifc.org/wps/wcm/connect/news_ext_content/ifc_external_corporate_site/news%2Band%2Bevents/news/ifc%2Bissues%2Bfirst%2Bgreen%2Bmasala%2Bbond%2Bon%2Blondon%2Bstock%2Bexchange\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">http://www.ifc.org/wps/wcm/connect/news_ext_content/ifc_external_corporate_site/news+and+events/news/ifc+issues+first+green+masala+bond+on+london+stock+exchange</a></p>\n                                "}, {"question": "Recently, our scientists have discovered a new and distinct species of banana plant which attains a height of about 11 metres and has orange-coloured fruit pulp. In which part of India has it been discovered?", "options": ["(a) Andaman Islands", "(b) Anaimalai Forests", "(c) Maikala Hills", "(d) Tropical rain forests of northeast"], "answer": "(a) Andaman Islands", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: A</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong>Musa indandamanensis, a sweet species of banana with orange pulp, has been discovered in the islands of Andamans.</p>\n<p>The banana species was found by a team of scientists from the Botanical Survey of India (BSI) from the Krishna Nalah tropical rain forest on the islands.</p>\n<p>It has also been reported by the scientists that the discovered species is thrice the size of a regular banana species</p>\n<p><a href=\"http://indiatoday.intoday.in/education/story/banana-species/1/498242.html\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">http://indiatoday.intoday.in/education/story/banana-species/1/498242.html</a></p>\n                                "}, {"question": "What is \u2018Greased Lightning-10 (GL-10)\u2019, recently in the news?", "options": ["(a) Electric plane tested by NASA", "(b) Solar-powered two-seater aircraft designed by Japan", "(c) Space observatory launched by China", "(d) Reusable rocket designed by ISRO"], "answer": "(a) Electric plane tested by NASA", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: A</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong>As per the NASA Website, it is in testing and development phase.</p>\n<p>The website says. \u201cImagine a battery-powered plane that has 10 engines and can take off like a helicopter and fly efficiently like an aircraft. That is a concept being developed by NASA researchers called Greased Lightning or GL-10.\u201d</p>\n<p><a href=\"http://www.nasa.gov/langley/ten-engine-electric-plane-completes-successful-flight-test\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">http://www.nasa.gov/langley/ten-engine-electric-plane-completes-successful-flight-test</a></p>\n                                "}, {"question": "The FAO accords the status of \u2018Globally Important Agricultural Heritage System (GIAHS)\u2019 to traditional agricultural systems. What is the overall goal of this initiative?\nTo provide modern technology, training in modern farming methods and financial support to local communities of identified GIAHS so as to greatly enhance their agricultural productivity\nTo identify and safeguard eco-friendly traditional farm practices and their associated landscapers, agricultural biodiversity and knowledge systems of the local communities\nTo provide Geographical Indication status to all the varieties of agricultural produce in such identified GIAHS\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below.", "options": ["(a) 1 and 3 only", "(b) 2 only", "(C) 2 and 3 only", "(d) 1, 2 and 3"], "answer": "(b) 2 only", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: B</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong><u>Statement 1 and 2:</u> In order to safeguard and support the world\u2019s agri- cultural heritage systems, in 2002 FAO started an initiative for the dynamic conservation of Globally Important Agricultural Heritage systems (GIAHS). So, clearly modern practices wouldn\u2019t be relevant to the initiative. 1 is incorrect.</p>\n<p><u>Statement 2:</u> The initiative intends to safeguard the social, cultural, economic and environmental goods and services of these heritage systems. So, 2 is correct.</p>\n<p><u>Statement</u> 3<u>:</u> There is no such provision. GI is accorded to products from a certain origin (e.g. Hyderabadi Biryani) and not to traditional agricultural systems.</p>\n<p><a href=\"http://www.fao.org/giahs/giahs-home/en/\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">http://www.fao.org/giahs/giahs-home/en/</a></p>\n                                "}, {"question": "Consider the following statements :\nNew Development Bank has been set up by APEC.\nThe headquarters of New Development Bank is in Shanghai.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?", "options": ["(a) 1 only", "(b) 2 only", "(c) Both 1 and 2", "(d) Neither 1 nor 2"], "answer": "(b) 2 only", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: B</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong>It was created by BRICS in 2014 and headquartered in Shanghai, China.</p>\n<p><a href=\"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_Development_Bank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_Development_Bank</a></p>\n                                "}, {"question": "What is \u2018Greenhouse Gas Protocol\u2019?", "options": ["(a) It is an international accounting tool for government and business leaders to understand, quantify and manage greenhouse gas emissions", "(b) It is an initiative of the United Nations to offer financial incentives to developing countries to reduce greenhouse gas emissions and to adopt eco-friendly technologies", "(c) It is an inter-governmental agreement ratified by all the member countries of the United Nations to reduce greenhouse gas emissions to specified levels by the year 2022", "(d) It is one of the multilateral REDD+ initiatives hosted by the World Bank"], "answer": "(a) It is an international accounting tool for government and business leaders to understand, quantify and manage greenhouse gas emissions", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: A</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong>The Greenhouse Gas Protocol (GHG Protocol) is the most widely used international accounting tool for government and business leaders to understand, quantify, and manage greenhouse gas emissions.</p>\n<p>It is a decade-long partnership between the World Resources Institute (WRI) and the World Business Council for Sustainable Development (WBCSD).</p>\n<p>It is working with businesses, governments, and environmental groups around the world to build a new generation of credible and effective programs for tackling climate change.</p>\n<p><a href=\"http://www.ghgprotocol.org/about-ghgp\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">http://www.ghgprotocol.org/about-ghgp</a></p>\n                                "}, {"question": "Which one of the following is the best description of \u2018INS Astradharini\u2019, that was in the news recently?", "options": ["(a) Amphibious warfare ship", "(b) Nuclear-powered submarine", "(c) Torpedo launch and recovery vessel", "(d) Nuclear-powered aircraft carrier"], "answer": "(c) Torpedo launch and recovery vessel", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: C</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong>It is Indian Navy\u2019s first totally indigenously-designed and built torpedo launch and recovery vessel.</p>\n<p><a href=\"http://www.thehindu.com/news/national/ins-astradharani-commissioned/article7730364.ece\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\"></a><a href=\"http://www.thehindu.com/news/national/ins-astradharani-\" rel=\"nofollow ugc\">http://www.thehindu.com/news/national/ins-astradharani-</a> commissioned/article7730364.ece</p>\n                                "}, {"question": "Regarding the taxation system of Krishna Deva, the ruler of Vijayanagar, consider the following statements:\nThe tax rate on land was fixed depending on the quality of the land.\nPrivate owners of workshops paid an industries tax.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?", "options": ["(a) 1 only", "(b) 2 only", "(c) Both 1 and 2", "(d) Neither 1 nor 2"], "answer": "(c) Both 1 and 2", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p></p><h1>Solution: C</h1>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong>Both the statements are correct.</p>\n<p><strong>Statement 1:</strong> Land revenue was the chief source of income. Land was divided into four categories for purposes of assessment, wet land, dry land, orchards and woods. Usually the share was one sixth of the produce. Land revenue could be paid in cash or kind. The rates varied according to the type of the crops, soil, method of irrigation, etc. So, 1 is clearly correct.</p>\n<p><strong>Statement 2:</strong> Besides land tax, many professional taxes were also imposed. There were on shopkeepers, farm servants, workmen, posters, shoemakers, musicians etc. There was also a tax on property. Grazing and house taxes were also imposed. Commercial taxes consisted of levies, duties and customs on manufactured articles of trade were also levied. Private owners of workshops paid an industries tax, which means 2 is correct.</p>\n<p><strong>Source: </strong>UB Singh \u2013 Administrative System in India: Vedic Age to 1947<a href=\"http://tinyurl.com/js458vk\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">http://tinyurl.com/js458vk</a></p>\n<p></p>                                "}, {"question": "Which one of the following books of ancient India has the love story of the son of the founder of Sunga dynasty?", "options": ["(a) Swapnavasavadatta", "(b) Malavikagnimitra", "(c) Meghadoota", "(d) Ratnavali"], "answer": "(b) Malavikagnimitra", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: B</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong></p>\n<ul>\n<li>It is a Sanskrit play by Kalidasa. It is based on some events of the reign of PushyamitraShunga.</li>\n<li>The play tells the story of the love of Agnimitra, the Shunga Emperor at Vidisha, for the beautiful hand-maiden of his chief queen.</li>\n</ul>\n<p><strong>Source</strong>: <a href=\"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/M%C4%81lavik%C4%81gnimitram\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/M%C4%81lavik%C4%81gnimitram</a></p>\n                                "}, {"question": "In which of the following regions of India are you most likely to come across the `Great Indian Hornbill\u2019 in its natural habitat?", "options": ["(a) Sand deserts of northwest India", "(b) Higher Himalayas of Jammu and Kashmir", "(c) Salt marshes of western Gujarat", "(d) Western Ghats"], "answer": "(d) Western Ghats", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: D</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong>Great Hornbills are found in three separate areas in South Asia; in the Western Ghats, the Himalayan foothills in Uttaranchal to south Nepal and Bhutan, and north-east India.</p>\n<p>They occur in primary evergreen and moist deciduous forest, mainly in lowland forest, but they can be found up to 2,000 meters in some areas.</p>\n<p>All other options apart from D can thus be easily eliminated.</p>\n<p><strong>Source</strong>: <a href=\"http://www.hornbills.in/great-hornbill.php\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">http://www.hornbills.in/great-hornbill.php</a></p>\n                                "}, {"question": "India is an important member of the \u2018International Thermonuclear Experimental Reactor\u2019. If this experiment succeeds, what is the immediate advantage for India?", "options": ["(a) It can use thorium in place of uranium for power generation", "(b) It can attain a global role in satellite navigation", "(c) It can drastically improve the efficiency of its fission reactors in power generation", "(d) It can build fusion reactors for power generation"], "answer": "(d) It can build fusion reactors for power generation", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: D</p>\n<p><strong>Justification</strong>:</p>\n<ul>\n<li>35 nations are collaborating to build the world\u2019s largest tokamak, a magnetic fusion device that has been designed to prove the feasibility of fusion as a large- scale and carbon-free source of energy based on the same principle that powers our Sun and stars.</li>\n<li>The ITER Members\u2014China, the European Union, India, Japan, Korea, Russia and the United States\u2014are now engaged in a 35-year collaboration to build and operate the ITER experimental device, and together bring fusion to the point where a demonstration fusion reactor can be designed.</li>\n</ul>\n<p><strong>Source</strong>: <a href=\"https://www.iter.org/proj/inafewlines\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">https://www.iter.org/proj/inafewlines</a></p>\n                                "}, {"question": "What was the main reason for the split in the Indian National Congress at Surat in 1907?", "options": ["(a) Introduction of communalism into Indian politics by Lord Minto", "(b) Extremists\u2019 lack of faith in the capacity of the moderates to negotiate with the British Government", "(c) Foundation of Muslim League", "(d) Aurobindo Ghosh\u2019s inability to be elected as the President of the Indian National Congress"], "answer": "(b) Extremists\u2019 lack of faith in the capacity of the moderates to negotiate with the British Government", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: B</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong>Difference between Moderates and Extremist plan of action against British was the primary reason for the Surat Split.</p>\n                                "}, {"question": "\u2018Doctors Without Borders (Medecins Sans Frontieres)\u2019, often in the news, is", "options": ["(a) a division of World Health Organization", "(b) a non-governmental international organization", "(c) an inter-governmental agency sponsored by European Union", "(d) a specialized agency of the United Nations"], "answer": "(b) a non-governmental international organization", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: B</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong>It is an international humanitarian-aid non-governmental organization (NGO) and Nobel Peace Prize laureate, best known for its projects in war-torn regions and developing countries facing endemic diseases.</p>\n<p>It was founded in France in response to the Biafran War (Nigerian Civil War).</p>\n<p><a href=\"http://www.doctorswithoutborders.org/about-us\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">http://www.doctorswithoutborders.org/about-us</a></p>\n                                "}, {"question": "Which of the following best describes the term \u2018import cover\u2019, sometimes seen in the news?", "options": ["(a) It is the ratio of value of imports to the Gross Domestic Product of a country", "(b) It is the total value of imports of a country in a year", "(c) It is the ratio between the value of exports and that of imports between two countries", "(d) It is the number of months of imports that could be paid for by a country\u2019s international reserves"], "answer": "(d) It is the number of months of imports that could be paid for by a country\u2019s international reserves", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: D</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong>Import Cover measures the number of months of money available in the national bank to cover the cost of imports.</p>\n<p>This is to avoid a BoP crisis, so that early preventive action can be taken. India has an import cover of around 12 months presently.</p>\n<p><strong>Source</strong>: <a href=\"http://articles.economictimes.indiatimes.com/2015-12-29/news/69379605_1_import-cover-foreign-exchange-reserves-import-bill\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">http://articles.economictimes.indiatimes.com/2015-12-29/news/69379605_1_import-cover-foreign-exchange-reserves-import-bill</a></p>\n                                "}, {"question": "There has been a persistent deficit budget year after year. Which action/actions of the following can be taken by the Government to reduce the deficit?\nReducing revenue expenditure\nIntroducing new welfare schemes\nRationalizing subsidies\nReducing import duty\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below.", "options": ["(a) 1 only", "(b) 2 and 3 only", "(c) 1 and 3 only", "(d) 1,2, 3 and 4"], "answer": "(c) 1 and 3 only", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p></p><div id=\"wpwrap\">\n<div id=\"adminmenumain\" role=\"navigation\" aria-label=\"Main menu\">\n<p>Solution: C</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong>Only statement 1 and 3 are correct.</p>\n<ul>\n<li><strong>Statement 1:</strong> Unnecessary revenue expenditure bloats the fiscal deficit, and since it forms the majority of government spending, its reduction has a very large effect on the fiscal deficit.</li>\n<li><strong>Statement 2:</strong> It will further increase the fiscal deficit.</li>\n<li><strong>Statement 3:</strong> Subsidies are a major component of government spending, and its reduction will cut down fiscal deficit.</li>\n<li><strong>Statement 4:</strong> It reduces tax revenue and thus increases fiscal deficit.</li>\n</ul>\n<p><strong>Source: </strong>NCERT 12<sup>th</sup> Macroeconomics</p>\n</div>\n</div>\n<p></p>                                "}, {"question": "Consider the following statements : The India-Africa Summit\nheld in 2015 was the third such Summit\nwas actually initiated by Jawaharlal Nehru in 1951\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?", "options": ["a) 1 only", "b) 2 only", "c) Both 1 and 2", "d) Neither 1 nor 2"], "answer": "a) 1 only", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p></p><ol>\n<li>\nSolution: A<p></p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong>India-Africa Summit started in 2008 (first summit) is one of the most spectacular diplomatic exercises hosted by India since the 1983 Non Aligned Movement (NAM) summit.</p>\n<p>Second and third summit were held in 2011 and 2015. So, 1 is correct and 2 is wrong.</p>\n<p><a href=\"http://www.idsa.in/idsacomments/3rd-india-africa-forum-summit_rberi_291015\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">http://www.idsa.in/idsacomments/3rd-india-africa-forum-summit_rberi_291015</a></p></li>\n</ol>\n<p></p>                                "}, {"question": "Recently, India\u2019s first \u2018National Investment and Manufacturing Zone\u2019 was proposed to be set up in", "options": ["(a) Andhra Pradesh", "(b) Gujarat", "(c) Maharashtra", "(d) Uttar Pradesh"], "answer": "(a) Andhra Pradesh", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: A</p>\n<p><a href=\"http://articles.economictimes.indiatimes.com/2015-09-21/news/66760948_1_andhra-pradesh-nimz-manufacturing-zone\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\"><strong>Justification: </strong></a><a href=\"http://articles.economictimes.indiatimes.com/2015-09-\" rel=\"nofollow ugc\">http://articles.economictimes.indiatimes.com/2015-09-</a> 21/news/66760948_1_andhra-pradesh-nimz-manufacturing-zone</p>\n                                "}, {"question": "With reference to \u2018Agenda 21\u2019, sometimes seen in the news, consider the following statements :\nIt is a global action plan for sustainable development\nIt originated in the World Summit on Sustainable Development held in Johannesburg in\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?", "options": ["a) 1 only", "b) 2 only", "c) Both 1 and 2", "d) Neither 1 nor 2"], "answer": "a) 1 only", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: A</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong>Agenda 21 is a non-binding, voluntarily implemented action plan of the United Nations with regard to sustainable development.</p>\n<p>It is a product of the Earth Summit (UN Conference on Environment and Development) held in Rio de Janeiro, Brazil, in 1992.</p>\n<p><a href=\"https://sustainabledevelopment.un.org/outcomedocuments/agenda21\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">https://sustainabledevelopment.un.org/outcomedocuments/agenda21</a></p>\n                                "}, {"question": "With reference to the economic history of medieval India, the term Araghatta\u2019 refers to", "options": ["(a) bonded labour", "(b) land grants made to military officers", "(c) waterwheel used in the irrigation of land", "(d) wasteland and converted to cultivated land"], "answer": "(c) waterwheel used in the irrigation of land", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: C</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong></p>\n<ul>\n<li><strong>Araghatta</strong>is a Persian wheel used in irrigation in medieval India.</li>\n<li>It is a mechanical device used to life water. It uses animal power to lift water from sources, especially from open wells. The animals used here are cattle, bullocks, etc.</li>\n<li><strong>Araghatta</strong>is made of ara + ghatta, ara means spoke and ghatta means pot</li>\n</ul>\n<p><strong>Source:</strong></p>\n<ol>\n<li><a href=\"http://base.d-p-h.info/en/fiches/dph/fiche-dph-7866.html\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">http://base.d-p-h.info/en/fiches/dph/fiche-dph-7866.html</a></li>\n<li><a href=\"http://tinyurl.com/zktanrk\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">http://tinyurl.com/zktanrk</a></li>\n</ol>\n                                "}, {"question": "The Montague-Chelmsford Proposals were related to", "options": ["(a) social reforms", "(b) educational reforms", "(c) reforms in police administration", "(d) constitutional reforms"], "answer": "(d) constitutional reforms", "explanation": "\n                                                                            <span class=\"wpProQuiz_respone_span\">\n\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tIncorrect\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t</span><br>\n                                    <p>Solution: D</p>\n<p><strong>Justification: </strong>They introduced by the British Government in India to introduce self- governing institutions gradually to India.</p>\n<p>They formed the basis of the Government of India Act 1919.</p>\n<p><a href=\"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Montagu%E2%80%93Chelmsford_Reforms\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Montagu%E2%80%93Chelmsford_Reforms</a></p>\n                                "}]}